<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth's triumph over deceit, or, A further demonstration that the people called Quakers be deceivers, and such as people ought to accompt accursed in their doctrines and principles in vindication of a former proof of that charge, made good against them, from the sorry shifts and evasions from it, and cavils of George Whitehead against it, in a pamphlet of his, called The Quakers no deceivers / written by John Horne ... as a further preservation of people from following any of their pernitious principles ...</title>
            <author>Horn, John, 1614-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44504</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41721</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355825</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355825</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44504)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1740:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth's triumph over deceit, or, A further demonstration that the people called Quakers be deceivers, and such as people ought to accompt accursed in their doctrines and principles in vindication of a former proof of that charge, made good against them, from the sorry shifts and evasions from it, and cavils of George Whitehead against it, in a pamphlet of his, called The Quakers no deceivers / written by John Horne ... as a further preservation of people from following any of their pernitious principles ...</title>
                  <author>Horn, John, 1614-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Allen ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, wormholed, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>"Eight queries propounded to Richard Hubberthorne, by John Horne"--p. 43-52.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723. --  Quakers no deceivers.</term>
               <term>Quakers no deceivers.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110700:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110700:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Truth's Triumph OVER DECEIT: OR A Further DEMONSTRATION that the people called <hi>Quakers</hi> be Deceivers, and ſuch as people ought to accompt accurſed in their Doctrines and Principles.</p>
            <p>In VINDICATION of A Former Proof of that Charge, made good againſt them for the ſorry ſhifts and evaſions from it, and cavils of <hi>George Whitehead</hi> againſt it, in a pamphet of his, called, <hi>The Quakers no Deceivers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> John Horne, <hi>Teacher at</hi> Lin-Alhallowes.</p>
            <p>As a further Preſervation of people from following any of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious principles, but that they might inquire after, and more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear to the truth of the Goſpel, as delivered in the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles in the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <q>
               <p>They have made lies their refuge, and under falſehood have they hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but the hail ſhall ſweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters ſhall over flow the hiding place.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 28.15, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But this I know, that the Lord is with me, becauſe mine enemy doth not try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over me.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm. 41.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Allen</hi> at the Riſing-Sun in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110700:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110700:2"/>
            <head>Truth's Tryumph over deceit.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eorge Whitehead</hi> hath made another ſcrible, in pretended anſwer to my book intituled, <hi>The Quakers proved Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> &amp;c. In which he doth but more manifeſt his folly and falſhood, as the more he ſcribles, the more it will yet appear, to ſuch as are not blinded with ignorance or errour. I ſhall, God aſſiſting, ſhew the reader briefly what pittifull ſtuff he hath, in ſome brief obſervations.</p>
            <p>That in his title he calls my charge unjuſt, and my book a pamphlet, and the people I preach to, <hi>Mooreans,</hi> or <hi>Vniverſalists,</hi> are but ſome over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings of the Gall of bitterneſſe that he is poſſeſt with, as alſo his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling my relation, a pretended and imperfect relation, and ſaying, that I falſly boaſt that I made good the charge, and of a pretended victory where I had none, which I leave to the judgement of the Lord, and of the auditory that heard our diſcourſe, though for the perfection and truth of my relation, <hi>George's</hi> inability to correct or contradict it in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of moment, in what he hath wrote againſt it, may paſſe with ſober men that hard us not, for a pretty good proof, or demonſtration. And as for his charging me with falſe doctrine, lyings, ſlanders, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the truth, I may give him leave in ſuch termes to vent his paſſion and never envie him for it, ſeeing God hath put him to rebuke before me, and the truth, notwithſtanding his ſerpent-like winding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to hide his deceits before his deluded followers tryumps over and againſt his errors.</p>
            <p>His preamble begins with truths wrongly applyed by him to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits: <hi>the Serpent and his ſubtilty which appeares againſt the ſeed of God, and againſt the power and wiſdom of God</hi>] is manifeſt in him and his party, <hi>and the torment and vexation which the ſtriving againſt the truth brings, and the confuſion and darkneſſe that overwhelmes them that ſo do</hi>] is evident enough to them that can ſee in this envious and imbittered people, who hiſs, like Serpents out of their holes, when the truth diſturbs them, and laies them open. How empty &amp; fooliſh a vapour it is that he ſaies, <hi>the Lord was with him, and by his ſtrength they were made able to tread upon their enemies.</hi> All that were at the diſpute (and remember how pitifully he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, ſo that he would needs, for want of any reaſonable anſwer, have left the argument, and fallen to read on our book, to begin ſome charge againſt us, inſtead of defending himſelf againſt my charge) may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110700:3"/>eaſily diſcern. I bleſſe the Lord, I was in my ſpirit clearly above his deceits, and my mouth was enlarged over him, and the people general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received ſatisfaction againſt him. His charging me with rage and madneſſe againſt the truth, becauſe I was courageous for it, againſt his deceits, and was ſo far from raging, that I rejoiced againſt him, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing moves me. I looke for an hundred worſe things from Satan than ſuch an aſpertion.</p>
            <p>But whereas he ſaith, he ſeveral times ſent to me, to come forth in publick before he could get me; take the truth of the thing, that thou maiſt (Reader) ſee his deecit herein. When <hi>George Fox</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged me to make good my charge, he bad me appoint time and place; I appointed mine own houſe, or <hi>Mr. Iohnſons,</hi> againſt which he excepted not, but only that time he ſaid he could not. Therefore when <hi>George Whitehead</hi> ſent to me to meet him, to do it either in the Market place or Steeple-houſe, or Steeple-houſe-yard, or ſtreets, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him anſwer, what <hi>George Fox</hi> and I had agreed on, as to that matter; and yet, that if they would procure the ſteeple-houſe, I would meet him there: this he refuſed, and then would have me meet him at <hi>Iſbel Barnards,</hi> which I told his friend, I ſhould not refuſe, if my friends judged it convenient, or becauſe he had upbraided me with my God, I was not unwilling to meete him in the market place, would my friends thither accompany me, and the Magiſtrates approve it; upon advice with my friends they were not willing I ſhould go to <hi>Iſbel Barnards</hi> or the Mraket-place. Then I ſent him word, that if he and his friends would joine with me and mine, in repairing the harmes might by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the meeting in the ſteeple-houſe, be done to the ſeats, I would joine with them in procuring it. But this alſo, though one of his own party judged it but reaſonable, he refuſed, becauſe he would not put his party upon any charge: then he deſired me to nominate ſome indifferent private houſe, ſeeing he judged mine not indifferent, and we judged <hi>Iſbel Bernards</hi> as little or leſſe indifferent; and I did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Mr. <hi>Philips</hi> his, where we ſhould have met, had his party, upon viewing of it, liked it; but the Church-warden in the mean while (without whoſe concent I would not make bold with the Church or ſteeple-houſe, or put either my friends or the pariſh upon the charge of repaires, they having been put to charge before at our former meeting by their occaſion) ſending me word that we might in the Chancel: ſo ſoon as we had that liberty granted, I ſent <hi>G. W.</hi> word of it, and accordingly there we met. Now judge Reader whether of us were moſt guilty of backwardneſſe to meete in the publick, ſo as was convenient, ſeeing I offered him ſo reaſonable, even in the judgement of ſome of his own party, and he refuſed it; but this is no new thing, to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and intimately accuſe others in deceit. He ſaies, <hi>The chief thing I drove at, was to make people believe, that there is no man living upon earth that ſinneth not, or can be perfectly freed from ſin in this life, and that the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them ſo long as they lived</hi>] which though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110700:3"/>it's not altogether true; becauſe the main thing, I drove at was not that, but to prove the <hi>Quakers</hi> deceivers. Yet thoſe things, he ſaies, I drove at, and would have people believe me in, are in part, that very words of the Prophets and holy men of God; and ſo if I drove at that to make people believe thoſe things, I drove but at the making them believe the truth of the Scriptures, in thoſe ſayings and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence <hi>George</hi> indeavoured to drive them from believing them. For, that there is not a juſt man upon earth that doth good and ſinneth not, and no man that ſins not, is not mine but <hi>Solomons</hi> by the ſpirit of truth, I trow, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.46. and that no man is perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly freed from ſin in all reſpects in this life, is evident both in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. and in that ſickneſſes, diſeaſes, and mortality that came in by ſin, abides upon all men till death, yea, and the bodily death that came in by ſin, abides upon all till the reſurrection: and ſo long as any fruit of ſin abides upon a man, he is not perfectly in all reſpects freed from ſin. And to ſay as he doth <hi>[that the aſſerting theſe things is the making way for my Fathers Kingdome which is upheld by ſin, as much as I could]</hi> is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent blaſphemy. For God being my Father (at leaſt by creation as he after, though erroniouſly ſaies, the Diſciples were taught ſo to call him their Father) his kingdome is not upheld by ſin; and if he calls him the Devil, he blaſphemes; or if he judge the Devil to be my Father, as no doubt his charity leads him, yet then he blaſphemes the ſpirit of truth which breathed in the holy men of God, while he makes the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting their ſayings a warring for the Devils kingdome, that they be their ſayings, the places above quoted with, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17, 20, 21, 22, 23. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8, 10. and 2.1, 2. make it evident. See Reader how this man diſcovers his ſhame and falſehood in al his oppoſitions, his intimations that we denyed him liberty to ſpeak in evidence of his (pretended) truths, is ſo falſe, that the contrary, namely that when he would have been reading, and at other times he was called upon again and again to anſwer, he would not for ſome time; yea, and ſometime he had liberty, or took it, to talke ſo much, that I could not have liberty to reply upon him, and the calling out of the company to him to anſwer or elſe own himſelf proved a deceiver, and perhaps ſometimes laughing at his folly, is that he calls the incivility towards him, and clamoring of many at once againſt him. And where he ſaies that, <hi>many hearing him with ſoberneſſe, was (as appeares) a grief to me, and probably ſome cauſe of my publiſhing of an imperfect relation of the diſcourſe in print to render him, and what he calls the truth, odious, and in my pride to make people believe I had got the victory.</hi> I avouch in the preſence of God, that the people hearing him with ſoberneſſe was no grief at all to me, or any thing that I ſee as making againſt me in the people, and if it appears ſo to him, it's becauſe his eye ſees by a falſe light, and the ſpirit of truth guids him not therein. I was very much rejoiced in the Lord to ſee his helpfulneſſe afforded me, and <hi>Geo. Whit.</hi> ſo made manifeſt to the people, and the people ſo ſatisfied: for which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110700:4"/>cauſe alſo I publiſhed as perfect a relation of the diſcourſe of theſe points ſpoken to, as poſſible I could, and could I poſſibly have come by every word, or fillable of it, I was not afraid nor aſhamed to make it publick, knowing right well the more perfectly it had been publiſhed, the more perfectly his folly had been made manifeſt: So that if what I have publiſhed in print render him odious, it is becauſe his folly and deceit in the diſpute was ſuch as deſerved it. As for what he ſaies, he ſhall make good againſt me in the ſtrength of God, it will appear to be but a deceived vapour in him by what I ſhall (through Gods aſſiſtance) ſay here to his two latter charges, which (he ſaies) his Treatiſe makes good, namely; That my Miniſtry, in which he (falſly) ſaies, <hi>I contend for ſin</hi> (<hi>juſt as the Apoſtle</hi> John <hi>did in</hi> 1 Joh. 1.8, 10. <hi>with</hi> 2.1.) <hi>is Anti-Chriſtian and both againſt the commands, promiſe and works of God, and leads to the making both the preaching and praying of Chriſt and the Saints inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, and that.</hi> 2. <hi>I (like a chollerick envious man againſt the truth of God and his people) am a forger of lies, a falſe accuſer and ſlanderer, and ſo one of the Dragons army, &amp;c.</hi> By this making good, or not making, thou maiſt judge Reader, whether the ſtrength of God be with him to make good his former againſt me by diſpute, which he could challenge me to in publick, either in market place, Steeple-houſe or their meeting houſe in <hi>Lin,</hi> namely. 1. <hi>That I am out of the ſteps of the true Miniſters, and am in the practice of deceivers, an hypocrite, and no Miniſter of Christ, and being a pariſh Priest am guilty of the Priests iniquity in many things againſt which I have declared. And</hi> 2. <hi>That I uphold a dead formal worſhip like the world, whereunto people are not called by the ſpirit of truth; which is not the true worſhip, and keep people from the life of God, and my Miniſtry for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and corrupt.</hi> Which his fooliſh challenge I ſhall not accept, both becauſe his folly and falſhood in his boaſts of ſtrength, to that may be ſufficiently diſcovered in his failers, of what he boaſts he hath done in his Treatiſe, as alſo becauſe he therein laies a trap for me, to get oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to reproach me; for he knowes I ſent him word, that I ſhould henceforth have no more to do with him, but according to the Apoſtles counſel reject them; now ſhould I accept his challenge, he and his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would reproach me, as they did upon a leſſe coloured occaſion as a lyer and falſe. Beſides theſe being perſonal charges, and the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of their anger againſt me, becauſe foiled at the diſpute, and ſuch things as theſe ſpoken ſo much as we thought needful in anſwer to his former book in which he ſpits ſuch venemous ſtuff againſt me, I ſhall not go about to plead my own cauſe, but leave it to God; and rather take good <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> courſe when <hi>Sennacherib</hi> railed upon him, that would not have him anſwered again.</p>
            <p>That he is far from making good his charges in the two other points of it ſpoken to, as he ſaies in his treatiſe, theſe things that follow in anſwer hereunto, I hope will fully evince.</p>
            <p>To my proofes for the Scriptures (which he only ſets down the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations without ſaying any thing to them particularly,) that the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110700:4"/>Prophets, Apoſtles, and holy men of God (even after they were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, and holy men) came confeſſing themſelves ſinners, and to have ſin. He ſaies, <hi>I have not made it appear that the</hi> Quakers <hi>do not ſo, for they own their confeſſing ſin, and they have confeſſed their ſins to the Lord as they did.</hi> To this I anſwer, that's evident enough that the <hi>Quakers</hi> do not boaſt by their not denying our charge againſt them in our firſt book, but pleading for their conceited ſinleſſeneſſe, and by what they ſay here; for, obſerve I pray, 1. They do but ſay, they own the Apoſtles and Prophets, confeſſing their ſins, ſeeing they ſay a man born of God hath no ſin to confeſſe, either then they deny the Apoſtles and Prophets, when ſuch, to have been born of God, or how do they own their confeſſing ſin? Nay, <hi>George</hi> ſaies, <hi>Paul</hi> (and he may as well ſay it of all the reſt) ſpake not of his own ſtate, but other mens.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What if they own their confeſſing ſins, that proves not that the <hi>Quakers</hi> do confeſſe them. The Scribes and Phariſees owned the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets doings, yet they did not as the Prophets. Thirdly, He ſayes they have confeſt them, that implies they do not ſo now. But the Apoſtles and Prophets do not ſay only they had in times paſt confeſt and forſaken them, but even when Apoſtles and Prophets confeſs them, in the preſent; ſee elſe <hi>David</hi> again and again as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. and 19. and 25. and 38. and 40. ſo <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 7.17, 20. We find no time of the Apoſtles and Prophets, while here, in which they ſaid, they had no ſin in them. But it ſeems the <hi>Quakers</hi> would be thought to be better than the Prophets and Apoſtles: As for their denying themſelves and ſin, I would they did as truly as pretend it, but their lying, falſifying, and paſſionate language, diſcovers the conntrary in them, for all their ſaying as this peice of <hi>Georges</hi> ſufficiently proves, his reproaching the Miniſters by the name of Prieſts, as he doth me often with much bitterneſſe, as Prieſt <hi>Horne,</hi> this Prieſt, this ſcornefull Prieſt, <hi>Horne,</hi> &amp;c. As they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue him not to have put off all malice, bitterneſſe, &amp;c. So are they not to be mattered by us; nor his reproaching any of us, as not forſaking our ſins, but pleading for them; its likely <hi>Davids</hi> enemies did ſo in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.15, 16, 17. to which <hi>George</hi> hath given no anſwer, though al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged to prove the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſuch towards us, as <hi>Davids</hi> enemies were to him. Doubtleſſe theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> would have accuſed the Apoſtles of not forſaking ſin too but pleading for it, had they lived in their time, and heard them ſay ſin dwelt in them, and that in many things they all offend, eſpecially they would have taxed <hi>David</hi> with it that is ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten confeſſing his ſin, as in part I have noted. But ſee how ſilly his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended proof is, that ſin doth not abide in all men the term of this life, and that they are out of the ſpirit and life of the Prophets and holy men of God, it is this, <hi>They know the fear of the Lord, which is to depart from iniquity, which fear keeps the heart clean, and ſuch as live in it ſhall not depart from the Lord,</hi> Jer. 32.40.] as if where men know, or have the fear of the Lord, there is no ſin in them, and as if to have ſin in a man, and to depart from the Lord, was all one. See the folly and falſehood
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110700:5"/>of this paſſage. Did not <hi>David</hi> know the fear of the Lord which <hi>is clean,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 19.9. <hi>the feare of the Lord is clean enduring for ever?</hi> or did he ſpeak at randome? and yet did not pray preſently after, <hi>cleanſe thou me from my ſecret ſins?</hi> or had not <hi>Paul</hi> the fear of the Lord, or did he depart from the Lord when he delighted in the Law of the Lord in his inner man, and yet found another law in his members, warring againſt the law of his mind? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.21, 22, 23. Doth not theſe paſſages evidence, that <hi>George Whitehead</hi> is ſo far from being in the ſtrength of God, as he boaſts, that he is a man of no judgement (that is, right underſtanding) that cannot diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſins being in men, and the heart departing from the Lord by ſin offending in a mans walking and leaving the way. How ſilly alſo it is that he accounts it abſurd for me to ſay, <hi>That people ought to account the</hi> Quakers <hi>accurſed, whom we have ſaid to be an heavy judgement of God to us in this Nation, for then they muſt count the judgement of God accurſed. And again pa.</hi> 11. <hi>That in ſtriving againſt, and reviling the</hi> Quakers, <hi>we ſtrive againſt and revile Gods judgement, when as we ſhould patiently bear Gods judgements?</hi> for doth not judgement begin at the houſe of God? 1 <hi>Pe.</hi> 4.17. and doth he not ordain wicked men for judgement, ſuch as the <hi>Caldeans? Heb.</hi> 1.12. and falſe teachers? <hi>Jude</hi> 4. yea, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan too, as to <hi>Job?</hi> and may we not accompt Satan his inſtruments ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, and yet not count Gods judgement ſo? or becauſe the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God is juſt and holy, are the wicked men ordained as a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holy and juſt too? If God ſhould judge a Nation by ſending wild beaſts among them, muſt they patiently let the wild beaſt devour their folkes, becauſe they be a judgement ſent of God? or elſe do they reſiſt the judgement of God? I trow not; its a judgement that we muſt be put to ſtrive againſt ſuch beaſts, and yet that judgement we may pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently bear in all our ſtrifts againſt them. Sure if G. W. cannot diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between the judgement of God as a judgement from him, and as to the conditions of the thing which he uſes as judgements, he is but a blind guide and they that follow him will fall into the ditch with him. Whereas I ſay, the true Apoſtles and Prophets never uſe to ſpeak of themſelves as finleſſe. G. W. <hi>ſaies its falſe, for the true Prophet ſaies, all his judgements were before me, and as for his ſtatutes I did not depart from them, I was alſo upright before him, and have kept my ſelfe from my iniquity,</hi> 2 Sam. 22.24. But mark here Reader, that <hi>David</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he had then iniquity, for how was iniquity his, if there was none in him, his keeping himſelf from it, is the ſame with that in the Apoſtle, of not walking after the fleſh, which alſo implies fleſh to be in them, and intice them that walk not after it. And <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks there of his innocency in reſpect of his carriages toward <hi>Saul</hi> and his other ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in the things they accuſed him in, and pretended as juſt cauſes of their perſecuting him, the Pſalm being pend upon that occaſion as the title ſhews, beſides which he committed many ſins, though yet then notwithſtanding it is ſaid of him, that he did that which was right in the eyes of the Lord, and turned not a ſide from any thing that he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110700:5"/>commanded him all the daies of his life, ſave only in the matter of <hi>Vriah</hi> the <hi>Hittite,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.5. But in thoſe things between him and his enemies, God rewarded him (not after his iniquitie which he kept himſelf from, as in another place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.10. he hath not dealt with us after our ſins, nor rewarded us after our iniquities; in which he acknowledges, even he among others, that they had ſins and iniquities, but they being kept from ſerving and living in them, God dealt not with them after them, but after the righteouſnes and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe found, according to the ſpirit or inward man; even as <hi>Paul</hi> when he had ſaid, he ſerved with his mind the Law of God, but with his fleſh the law of ſin; yet adds, there is therefore no condemnation to them that walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit; God therein deals with them according to their cleanneſſe in Chriſt, and in their walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the ſpirit, and not after their ſin in their members: ſo that quotation alſo clearly failes him. It is true too that God promiſes that his people ſhall be all righteous, and clean from all their filthineſſe; yea, and they are righteous in Chriſt, and his blood actually and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally cleanſeth them; but that proves not that the Saints and Prophets ever boaſted themſelves to be without ſin: But even they that ſaid, the blood of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin, ſay too imediately after, if we ſay we have no ſin we deceive our ſelves; nay, ſeeing Gods afflicting his people, is to purge away their ſin, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.8, 9. and the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations he tries them with, are to try and purifie their faith from the mixtures therein, (both of them being as baptizings with water and fire to thoſe ends) it appeares, that ſo long as they are ſubject to afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and tryals, (which is ſo long as they live, death it ſelf being one way of afflicting and trying) they have droſſe and uncleanneſſe to be purged from, and God is performing his promiſes to them therein, that they may be all perfectly righteous even in themſelves, in the new heaven and earth and new Jeruſalem, where ſhall be no unclean thing, and where ſhall be the full accompliſhment of Gods righteouſneſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, to which alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. alludes. As for thoſe that <hi>John</hi> ſaw <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. that were without fault before the Throne of God, and that could ſing to the Lord a new ſong, I ſay all that heartily believe in Chriſt, and are not moved away from the hope of the Goſpel, it is Chriſts office to preſent them holy unblameable and without reproof in Gods ſight, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.22.23. not becauſe they are ſinleſs in themſelves, but becauſe they are in him who is their perfect righteouſneſſe; nor is that the new ſong they ſing, that in us is no fault or blame; but while they accuſe themſelves and confeſſe their ſins, he is juſt and faithful and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives them, and ſo preſents them in himſelf without blame before God, and their ſong is praiſes or ſalvation to the Lord, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.23. <hi>David</hi> ſung that new ſong, and yet complained of innumerable ſins, and evils compaſſing him about in himſelf: See elſe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.11, 12, 13. So that ſtill here appears in <hi>George</hi> nothing but ignorant miſtakes, or the ſpirit of deceit. He adds, <hi>that that ſong cannot be ſung by thoſe that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110700:6"/>are in their iniquities, and pleading for ſins, being enemies to the ſtate of the new creature.</hi> But he herein groſly prevaricates and deceives his Reader, confounding mens having ſin in them, and confeſſing their ſins with men being in ſin, and pleading for it; between which is a vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: <hi>Paul</hi> was not in his ſin, but in Chriſt, nor did he plead for ſin, but ſtrive againſt it and deny it, when he ſaid, ſin was in him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed that he did what he would not. We ſay not then, that the true Apoſtles and Prophets were in ſin, and pleaded for it, but had ſin in them, and bewailed their ſins; nor do we in ſo ſaying, plead for ſin, no more than they did. Therefore <hi>George</hi> herein bewrayes his great ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and miſtake, and his concluſion is meer vanity and deceit, <hi>viz. That they have a cloud of witneſſes, and many evidences for their teſtimonie that it is of God, and that what they hold is truth, and that all that own God muſt own them herein.</hi> Which is all falſe, as by what is ſaid may be ſeen.</p>
            <p>I ſayd, that when <hi>John</hi> ſaid, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.17. As he is ſo are we in this world, he could not mean it, we are without ſin, becauſe that's contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his own expreſſions, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8. This G. W. railes on me for, and adds, <hi>That</hi> John <hi>who knew the ſtate in which they had ſin, and in which if they ſaid they had no ſin, they deceived themſelves, &amp;c. did not ſay they ſhould have ſin ſo long as in the world, for he ſaith, little children let no man deceive you, he that doth righteouſneſſe is righteous, as he is righteous,</hi> 1 John 3.6, 7. Plainly implying that they are deceivers that ſay, men cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin while they are in the World, &amp;c. Mind Reader the wildneſs of his anſwers, &amp; how he leaves my ſaying undiſproved, do what he can; for what if <hi>Iohn</hi> did not ſay in expreſſe words, that they ſhould have ſin ſo long as they were in this world; Seeing that Scripture ſpeaks of what they were at preſent (as he is, ſo we are in this world?) it's enough to proove, that what <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid there, of their preſent ſtate, may not be interpreted as the <hi>Quakers</hi> do, that they were then without ſin, ſeeing it croſſes what he ſaid before of their preſent eſtate, in that reſpect. And what though he that doth righteouſnes is righteous, even as he is righteous; that proves not that he that doth righteouſneſſe hath no ſin in him, for he that confeſſes his ſins, doth righteouſneſſe therein, otherwiſe how is it righteouſneſſe and faithfulneſſe in God to forgive him, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. So then he that, in ſuch a ſenſe as in that, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. confeſſeth his ſins, is righteous as Chriſt is righteous, for Chriſt is his righteouſneſſe; and yet he that confeſſeth his ſin, is not without ſin in himſelfe, for then he ſhould confeſſe a falſehood: And what though (as he adds) that in 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17. <hi>have relation to their dwelling in God and God in them</hi> (that's but <hi>George's</hi> affirmation) do not they that walke in the light, as he is in the light, dwell in God, and God in them? and yet have ſins that the blood of Chriſt cleanſeth them from: and if they ſayd, they have no ſin, they deceive themſelves, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.7, 8. I ſay, the true Apoſtles &amp; Prophets uſed not to glory in their perfection, and finleſneſſe. He anſwers. <hi>Then they uſed not to glory in Chriſt, and who is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110700:6"/>it that will believe this deceit, for Chriſt was their righteouſneſſe and perſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> See Reader, what a deceitful man is this, that leaves out the word ſinleſneſſe, which I added on purpoſe, to ſhew what perfection I meant of, and then to ask if the Apoſtles gloried not in a perfection, which he was ſure I meant not of, for though Chriſt be by the gift of God their perfection, yet he is not their perſonal ſinleſneſſe or ſelfe perfection, that I ſpake of; theſe men are good at little, but at crafty catching at, and perverting expreſſions.</p>
            <p>Again, to our ſaying they reproached us, for owning our ſelves part of the Nation, guilty of ſin with them. He taxeth us, <hi>For finding fault with the Teachers and people, and yet now we are joyned with them, and guilty of ſin with them, and that I joine my ſelf with the blind watchmen, and dumb dogs, and then taxe us with hypocriſie and deceit, for one while de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring againſt the Teachers, and people of the Nation, and another while to joine with them.</hi>] But marke Reader, that I ſaid not we joined our ſelves with them in their ſinning, but in confeſſing ſins; that is, we conſeſſe ours with theirs, nor ſay we, that we are guilty of all their ſins, but guilty of ſin. And will not his charges of us, for this, fall upon the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> did not he one while inviegh againſt the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and the people, yea many times, and yet another while joine in himſelf among them, in confeſſing the Nations ſins, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.10, 11, 12, 13. when he ſaid, we grope for the wall like the blind, and we grope as if we had no eyes, and our tranſgreſſions are multiplyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and our ſins teſtifie againſt us. Did <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeak thoſe things of himſelf and the Diſciples, as a diſtinct party from the body of the Nation, or as joining in the Nation with themſelves? If as a diſtinct party, would not <hi>George</hi> ſay then, they were hypocrites for faulting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and being as bad themſelves? If as joining themſelves in with the Nation, were they not guilty of the ſame that <hi>George</hi> throwes upon us, if we be therefore guilty, as he ſaies? Surely all that read theſe things, may ſee herein G. W.'s weakneſſe. My charges of them denying Chriſt to have that body glorified in heaven, in which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, is not diſproved by my ſaying, they granted the ſame body that ſuffered was glorified at Gods right hand, becauſe (as elſewhere we have cleared it) they meant equivocally in that ſaying, and not of the perſonal body of Chriſt: but to that and their denyal of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of mens bodys, we have ſpoken fullyer, in our anſwer to their book againſt us. Nor will my ſaying, they are perſons of no judgement in theſe things, ſave them from being guilty of indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſubvert the faith about them, ſeeing judgement, in Scripture expreſſion, ſignifies right underſtanding, as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.14. and 59.8. and they that have no underſtanding to do good, may be wiſe to do evil, as the Prophet ſaies. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.22.</p>
            <p>To that of our Saviour, Be ye perfect as your heavenly Father is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, alledged by G. W. to proove, that ſome men are without ſin here. I noted, That men may in Scripture ſenſe be ſaid to be perfect, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110700:7"/>have ſin in them. Inſtancing in <hi>Job.</hi> and <hi>Aſa.</hi> And 2. That exhortations to things, prove not thoſe things to be perfectly attained by any here, nor doth the Scripture ever ſay, Let not ſin be in you, &amp;c. The firſt of theſe <hi>George</hi> paſſes over, which, would he have defended himſelfe to purpoſe he ſhould not have done. To the 2. he ſaies, <hi>To what end or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect then was his exhortation? What, muſt men be under the commands after death which they had in their life time, and not till then fulfill them? here's darkeneſs indeed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>made manifeſt, and the command put a far off.</hi> To that conſider, are all commands to no end and effect, that are not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled by them to whom they are given? Sure then many commands given of God, muſt be concluded to be ſo, for how many commands of his are broken by men, &amp; not fulfilled of them? <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.29. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.23. Shall we ſay therefore they were to no end or effect? Sure his end is that we ſhould preſſe, in his ſtrength, after what is commanded, to our abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, knowing that he accepts through Chriſt our endeavour, though we attain not here its perfection: and that where we are ſhort we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, and in the ſenſe of it, being humbled in our ſelves, give glory to God, in, and for Chriſt, in whom we are (and by whom we ſhall be made) perfect; as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelfe, to will was preſent with him, even to will all that the commandment requires, but how to perform it, he found not: yet was not the commandment without end or effect, in as much as in the inner man, he delighted in it and groaned for the day of perfect liberty, when there ſhould be no let to do it perfectly; and thanked God in Chriſt Jeſus, in whom he being perfect, was not under condemnation, for what he found not; as for being under commands after death, I ſay men ſhall fulfill command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments after death given in this life; for muſt not the ſpirits of juſt men love God after the bodily death and in the reſurrection? yea, ſhal they not then love him with all their heart, more perfectly than now they do, when they more perfectly injoy him? And yet they are commanded now to love him. So that the darkneſſe appears in G. W. To the other, that the Scripture ſaies not any where, Let not ſin be in you. He ſaies, <hi>Is it not all one to ſay, be ye perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect, or waſh you, make yee clean, keep Gods command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, love and ſerve him with all the heart, which muſt be fulfilled: then what part of man muſt be a ſubject for ſin to dwell in while he lives here?</hi>] To the firſt of theſe, the ſaying, Be ye perfect, &amp;c. Is not the ſaying, Let not ſin be in you? Thoſe words are not theſe, &amp; no more neceſſarily included in them, than, Let no weakneſſe, infirmity or mortality be in you, or no ignorance of any thing in heaven or earth; ſeeing God is as perfectly free from them, as from ſin: but the ſayings of Scripture are to be interpreted according to their ſcope, which there appears to be perfect in teſtifying or extending love to enemies, as well as friends, as God doth. As God is ſo perfect in charity, as to love and do good to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and good, ſo would Chriſt have his diſciples in an anſwerable ſenſe, which how G. W. and the <hi>Quakers</hi> faile in their bitterneſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches ſufficiently evidence. Nor is it all one to ſay, Waſh you, make
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110700:7"/>you clean, and let no ſin be in you; for theſe phraſes alluding to the waſhings under the Law; as it was not one and the ſame there, to ſay, Waſh you from ſome uncleanneſſe defiling the fleſh, and let no ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean or defiling humor, as of blood or other matter, be in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; for the cleaneſt body had ſuch humors in it, as, iſſuing out upon it, would defile it: So, neither is it all one to ſay, Waſh you from your ſins and defilements (which is done in confeſſing and denying them) and let no ſin be in you; the being of ſin in men, being not imputed, were not conſented to, or ſided with, no more than the being of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean humors within the body, were accounted to men when they did not iſſue out, to touch and ly upon the body. As <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25. and 8.1. Nor is it all one to ſay, Keep the commandments, love God with all the heart; for that requires no more, as to Gods gracious acceptation, than that as he is in the light, we walk in the light, and love him with all the ability of knowing and loving here given us; which is not, while here, ſo perfect as to have no ignorance of God, and ſo no ſin in us; however thoſe ſayings are not that. To that queſtion, In what part muſt ſin dwell, &amp;c. I ſay ſin will, whither we will or no, dwell in our members while they be mortal. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17.20. with <hi>Pſalm</hi> 143.2. So as no man living, ſhould God enter into judgement with him, can be juſtified in his ſight, which, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſaies next<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Proves not that the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them while they lived, and ſeeing the Scripture it ſelfe doth not prove it, he ſaies, it's no matter of my word, who</hi> (he ſaies) <hi>perverts the Scripture</hi> therein, both belying me and the Scripture, for the Scripture gives this as the reaſon wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>David</hi> would not that God ſhould enter into judgement with him, though his ſervant, that no man living ſhould be juſtified in his ſight. Doth not, no man living, include no Prophet or Apoſtle, as men while here living, Suitable to that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.3. if thou Lord mark iniquities, Lord who ſhall ſtand? as implying none ſhould. So that Scripture proves what I aſſerted, unleſſe the Apoſtles and Prophets could be proved not to have been men ſo long as they lived.</p>
            <p>He ſaies, <hi>That Scripture includes not the Saints, as to prove them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtified, who were changed from that ſtate wherein no man living could be juſtified in the ſight of God, and were come through the death and the many tryalls and tribulations into the life and righteouſneſſe of Chriſt.</hi>] See here, Reader, if this man hath any thing but deceit? And is it a matter for his words without Scripture proofe? Was not <hi>David</hi> a Saint, when the ſervant of the Lord, and deſires God to anſwer him in his faithfulneſs and righteouſneſſe? who is the accuſer of the Saints here, but G. W. that implies, that <hi>David</hi> was not a Saint? or is no man living a Saint? Muſt they ſtay from being Saints till they are dead and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized by the <hi>Pope?</hi> If the Saints while they live here be men that live, then cannot they be juſtified if God ſhould enter into judgement with them; either then ſay, that the Saints are not men living, while here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110700:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>or that <hi>David</hi> ſaid falſe, or elſe that G. W, is a deceiver, and not to be liſtened to by us. And yet we ſay not, that the Saints be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded as to be unjuſtified while here, but that is not becauſe they could be juſtified, ſhould God enter into judgement with them, though he may judge them through him; he deals not with them immediately, as, or according to what they are in themſelves, or according to their ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.10, 11. But in, and according to his good will in Chriſt, what he ſpeaks of a ſtate in which they are come through the death, &amp;c. What be they but his additions to the Scriptures, of which <hi>Davids</hi> ſaying gives no intimation. Is there any Saint living here in any ſtate that is not a man living? or is it ſaid, no man in the death, or that is, not yet paſſed through the death, can be juſtified? Alas, what be theſe things, but ſorry deceitful evaſions from plain truth. He ſaies, <hi>I relate part of our diſcourſe deceitfully and imperfectly,</hi> and yet after que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, whether I relate it or not, and then laies down part of what is related about <hi>Pauls</hi> groning to be delivered, &amp;c. But wherein I relate it imperfectly, much leſſe deceitfully, he ſhowes not, only ſaies, I have belyed and wronged his words and left out the greateſt part of them that cleared his anſwer: and yet afterwards ſaies, he could not have liberty to open what he ſaid ſo much there as here; and yet if the Reader compare what I related, with the ſum of what he ſaies here, where he took his own liberty aſſuredly, without moleſtation from us, he will find, that beſides his quotations and perverſions of what he quotes from <hi>John, Jeremy</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſa.</hi> of which he then made no mention, I clearly laid down the ſubſtance of his ſayings, and that he could not have liberty there to clear his ſayings, is ſo far from truth, that we often urged him to anſwer, and he was ſo void of any clearing anſwer, that he would have left the argument to read on our book what did nothing concerne it. And that I have caſt no lye nor ſcornfull ſlander upon him in ſaying, he was baffled (as he here charges me) may be evident from this, that to my demand of him, Whether the Apoſtles and Prophets, were not Apoſtles and Prophets when as he granted, they confeſt they had ſin: he denies not that he granted, yea, nor that to my queſtioning, what ſtate it was, then of which he ſaid they had a time and ſtate that they had no ſin: he replied, when they were born of God, nor that to my queſtion whether they were not born of God when Apoſtles and Prophets? he anſwered, that they (as <hi>Paul</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) had a time when not born of God, <hi>viz.</hi> when he groaned and travelled, waiting for the adoption, nor doth he deny, that he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to clear up that, that he was not born of God while he ſo waited for the redemption of the body, only faults me for not giving a full relation of what he ſaid to it: now then I do demand, if he was not baffled, to what purpoſe did he (upon my quoting 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. to prove that he was born of God all the time he was an Apoſtle) fly to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other anſwer; that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake to conditions below his own? If he was not quite beat off his other anſwer, why fled he to this? which cannot
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110700:8"/>be true and the other too: For if <hi>Paul</hi> was but then groaning to be born, and not born of God, then ſpake he of his own ſtate, and if he ſpaek to others ſtates below his own then, then is it not true that he had, while an. Apoſtle, or then when he ſaid, he ſo waited a time in which he was not born of God, ſo theſe two ſhifts clearly overthrow one the other. And whereas he ſaies, <hi>many that heard the diſpute can witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me for impudent belying and ſlandring him.</hi> I call God to witneſſe, in whoſe preſence I am, and dare appeal to all indifferent and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Auditors, that I have not in any thing belyed or ſlandered him, much leſſe impudently. Let us ſee what he himſelf ſaith he ſaid, <hi>Paul witneſſed,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the groaning and travelling in pain before the birth was born in him, or before he was born of God, or in the ſtate of him that was born of God.</hi> (Mark Reader his own inconſtancy and confuſion, as not knowing how to phraſe it) intending (ſaith he) as 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. who cannot ſin, it ſeems he was ſo baffled that he could not then tell us his intention, nor now doth explain here thoſe in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. are ſaid to be born of God, only ſeems to imply, that he thinks there be other kinds of being born of God than that ſpeaks of, which would or could he have cleared himſelf, he ſhould have proved, and not ſo ſpoken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction and underſtanding. He adds, <hi>that</hi> Paul <hi>could ſin, when he could do the evil he would not</hi>] which yet he proves not, ſeeing he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaies, it was not he that did it, but ſin that dwelt in him, and to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that the fleſh luſting againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit againſt the fleſh, they could not do what they would, and ſo it was there with him, as the law in his members, warring againſt the law in his minde, he could not do what in his ſpirit he would, ſo the inner man or ſpirit delighting in the law of God, and luſting againſt the fleſh or law in his members, he could not do what his fleſh would, and what ſin in him did: yea, what his members or fleſh, and ſo he (as denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by it) did, he as in the ſpirit, or according to the inner man (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which <hi>John</hi> ſaies, whoſoever is born of God cannot ſin) could not do. What he adds about <hi>his travelling in pain for deliverance from the bondage of corruption, and that where the ſon or birth from above is born, the glorious liberty of the Sons of God is injoyed, which the creatures waited for, and the travelling in pain for deliverance is ceaſed, as alſo the firſt clauſe of his ſaying above related, that</hi> Paul <hi>witneſſed the groaning and travelling in pain before the birth was born in him.</hi> Is all beſides the buſh, as in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the diſcourſe alſo is evidenced, for as I then and there cleared it, what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies of travelling in pain and of deliverance from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of corruption, into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, he ſaies of the whole creation, diſtinguiſhing himſelf and the Sons of God, who had then received the firſt fruites of the ſpirit from the creature before ſpoken of, as is clear, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20, 21, 22, 23. for he ſaies, not only they, but we our ſelves alſo that have the firſt fruits of the ſpirit, even we our ſelves groan within our ſelves, waiting for the adoption, the redemption of the body. It's clear, that the Apoſtles there, in <hi>ver.</hi> 19, 20. &amp;c. ſpeakes of the reſtitution of all things ſpoken of by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110700:9"/>(as <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. When the glory of the Sons of God, that now ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with Chriſt (as <hi>ver.</hi> 17.) even to the bodily death, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; and when the creature it ſelf, as diſtinct from them, even the fabrick of the world ſhall be renewed and freed from the bondage of corruption, that it is by occaſion of mens ſins ſubjected to in hope, for which freedome in it's kind, it groans and travels together till now, and for the redemption of the body, then alſo to be effected, from the bondage, to what it ſuffers now, and ſhall lye under, in ſome things till then, they the Sons of God diſtinct from the other creatures, alſo wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, groaned; what groaning or travelling was neceſſary to precede the being born of God,
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.12, 13.</note> ſo as to be made Sons of God, <hi>Paul</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy Apoſtles and Prophets had it in their receiving Chriſt, before they were made Apoſtles and Prophers, though I deny not but in that birth there might be degrees and growth after, nor will the perfection of it, be as to the body till the reſurrection thereof from the dead: So that yet it abides firme, that <hi>Paul,</hi> when born of God, confeſſed he had ſin dwelt yet in him. Whereas he adds, <hi>That I perverted his compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that it was not intended to prove that</hi> Paul <hi>was not born into the world according to the fleſh wherewith he travelled, &amp;c.</hi> I anſwer, that G. W. groſly plaies the Sophiſter in repreſenting me as wreſting his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to any ſuch intention. It's evident what I ſaid is to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that as no woman travells with natural children before ſhe her ſelfe be born, and be a woman; So neither did <hi>Paul</hi> groan for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body, till himſelf was born of God in the mind and ſpirit, and ſo that he was born of God, when he ſo groaned as he there ſpeaks of. His quotation of <hi>John</hi> 16.21, 22. is impertinent, for Chriſt ſpeaks there of the ſorrow they had before the ſpirit was powred down upon them, before they were ſent out into all the world, as <hi>Act.</hi> 1.8. with <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. which <hi>Paul</hi> had before he was an Apoſtle, and ſo before he made that confeſſion of ſin,
<note place="margin">Act. 9.17.</note> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17.20. or elſe alſo of their having ſorrow in travelling to bring forth the knowledg of Chriſt in others, and their joy after in their being brought forth unto God, and moſt fully when they ſhal be preſented with them, together at the great appearance of Chriſt in his glory at the reſurrection of the juſt, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13, 14. that in <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.6. ſpeaking of <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſorrow in captivity, and their joy in their return again, is yet more imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently alledged by him, and ſo is that in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. abuſed; for the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> doth not witneſſe as <hi>George</hi> pretends, that in them a child was born, &amp; in them a ſon was given; but to them, which he ſpeaks prophetically of Chriſt given in the counſel, purpoſe and promiſe of God, and to be born in his time, which he ſpeaks of, for its certainty as if then accompliſhed, though not to themſelves, but to us in theſe after ages, they miniſtred the things now preached as accompliſhed; as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11, 12. His confuſion in ſaying one while, <hi>The Diſciples travelled in ſorrow before the man, or birth from above, was born in them, and preſently, that they were in pain before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110700:9"/>that birth,</hi> I paſſe, as alſo his judging me as ignorant of the ſtates he ſpeaks of, their talking of a babe in them, faſhioning their bodies to the likeneſſe here of Chriſts glorious body, I have writ and yet do teſtifie againſt, as arguing their unbelief, and denyal of the reſurrection of the body, and the power of Chriſt thereto, which makes them turne the things thereabout into fancies and allegories of their own divifing, which ſhews them to be ſuch as ſubvert the faith, and ſuch as are to be counted accurſed. That, <hi>I wickedly belyed the people in ſaying they all laught, becauſe many of his friends, and others that were ſober minded did not join with them, &amp;c.</hi> Is as falſe as that <hi>Mathew</hi> wickedly belyed the people of <hi>Judea</hi> and about <hi>Jordan,</hi> in ſaying all <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions about <hi>Jordan</hi> went out to <hi>John,</hi> and were baptized of him, when it appears that the Phariſees rejected the counſel of God, and were not baptized of him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5, 6. with <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. I diſtinguiſhed the people both from his friends and our ſelves, but are his friends no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber minded men, that they are diſtinguiſhed from them; I ſpeak of the generality of the people, if there were one or two did otherwiſe, it's more then I obſerved.</p>
            <p>To that of, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. Whoſoever believes that Jeſus is the Chriſt is born of God. he cavils that I did it without underſtanding and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction, whereas it was his part being the anſwer, to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, if he underſtood any ground for it, and not mine, who was opponent; but ſomething he will ſay, though to no purpoſe, how much more truly might I have ſaid, what he charges me with, of the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his own quotations in his anſwer, as that in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17. and yet when in my poſtſcript I diſtinguiſhed of that in 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. He ſnatches at the firſt part of my diſtinction, (<hi>viz.</hi> that whoſoever is perfectly born of God (as the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, and the men themſelves in the Reſurrection) cannot ſin at all; but none ſo perfectly born of God here) taking no notice of the other propoſitions that ſpeak of men, as here born of God, and then cries out. <hi>Oh what pittiful ſtuffe is here to imagine men are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly born of God, ſo as not to ſin till deceaſed; this would make the worke of God imperfect here, when all his works are perfeci;</hi> &amp; then taxes me as if I had ſaid, that <hi>thoſe that were born of God in the Apoſtles daies, were ſome that were deceaſed and riſen again.</hi> Whereas I in the other part of the diſtinction ſhewed how thoſe that are born of God, while here, may be ſaid not to ſin, and that they cannot ſin; but why is it ſuch pittifull ſtuffe, to ſay, that the ſpirits of juſt men deceaſed, &amp; the men themſelves when rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, are, or ſhall be, more perfectly born of God, the while here living? do they gain no degree of perfection by death? where then is the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage they have by it? Nor ſhall they gain none in the reſurrection neither, when ſeeing him as he is, they ſhall be like him? 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. or have the preſent propoſitions of truth, all their fulfilling at the preſent? He that hath the Son hath life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. Have they not ſo that are deceaſed in him? and ſhall they not have him, and life more fully
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110700:10"/>in the reſurrection, if G. believe it? And why muſt the work of God be imperfect, if men be not perfectly born of God here? was the work of God, all whoſe works are perfect, imperfect when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, not that I am already perfect, or have already attained? <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.12. or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Fathers dyed in the faith, not having received the promiſes God, having provided ſome better thing for us, that they without us ſhould not be made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.39. Were the works of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore imperfect till theſe laſt ages? If ſo, then why not ſo too till the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? If they were perfect alwaies, and in all generations, then mens not being perfectly born of God, while here, hinders not their perfection, no more then <hi>Pauls</hi> or the Fathers being not perfect did. Surely G. W. is very ſilly, if he think as he writ here, and a very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, if he thought otherwiſe, and they be ſimple that are catcht with ſuch chaff, or worthy to be blind ſtill that will not ſee it, but let us ſee what diſtinction he hath deviſed upon, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. to ſave his credit. He ſaies, <hi>It's true according to</hi> Johns <hi>teſtimony of a true believer, who by faith hath victory over the world, and ſo being born of God, is not under the bondage of corruption, &amp;c. But ſuch he ſaies I. H. doth not own while men are here.</hi>] Folly and falſehood, folly, for he implies, that <hi>Johns</hi> ſaying is not true without diſtinction, and yet <hi>John</hi> ſaid it without diſtinction; for he ſaid not, whoſoever ſo, or ſo, believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt, but in general expreſſions whoſoever believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt is born of God. True it is that he ſaies <hi>ver.</hi> 4. whatſoever is born of God overcometh the world, and this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith, but then in <hi>ver.</hi> 5. he explicates what their faith was anſwerable to, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. ſaying, who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believes that Jeſus is the Son of God, which is all one with whoſoever believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt; clearly fignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he that believeth that, is born of God, and ſo overcometh the world, even the ſpirit, rudiments, and pollutions of the world ſo as none elſe: and that they who believe not (that is, with their heart believe not) that Jeſus (even that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> whom the Jews crucified bodily, and God raiſed from the dead (for heſides him the Apoſtles did preach no other Jeſus, name, or thing, within men or without men to be the Saviour, or ſalvation of God to be believed on, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.10, 11, 12.) is the Chriſt the Son of God, the Saviour of the world, the annointed one to bring us back to God, the propitiation for our ſins, the righteouſneſſe and life given us of God; I ſay he implies that they who believe not him to be the Chriſt, or annointed Saviour, in, and through, what he hath done and ſuffered for us in the body of his fleſh, and is become for us therethrough, and is doing for us in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on Gods right hand, as the great Mediator and high Prieſt for us, and from heaven, to, and in us, as the great Apoſtle and Prophet of our profeſſion, and Lord of all; and in what he is appointed to do, and will do at his glorious deſcent from heaven, and appearing, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then to be revealed in glory; they have not, nor do overcome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110700:10"/>the world: But whatever be their pretences and appearances to men of being out of, and above the world, they are overcome of the world and are in the worlds ſtate; being led of and by the god of the world and rudiments of it, which lead men that ſeek after righteouſneſs and hope toward God, to ſeek it in themſelves and their doings, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications and frames; but not to go out of themſelves into Chriſt and his name, to accept of him (even that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> as made ſin for them, and raiſed again for their juſtification, and glorified at Gods right hand) for their wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, holyneſſe and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo to have their rejoycing in him, and expectation from him, and of him, at his appearing: they who have ſo received him and abide in him, are indeed born of God, and have overcome the world: But they that do not ſo receive him, are in and of the world, who neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and counting faith in him fooliſhneſſe, live and rejoice in their own good meanings, honeſty, zeal, blameleſneſſe, mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and devotions, as the Phariſees and ſome falſe Apoſtles did, who yet were of the world, though they had avoluntary humility and ſhew of wiſdome therein, in neglecting the body, &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18, 23. And much men may have that way, and great appearance of having over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world, becauſe they can, and do deny themſelves of many groſſer comforts and vanities of it, and indure much voluntary hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or ſufferings from others of it, as the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.28, 40. And the old Philoſophers, and wordly religious amongſt both <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> who alſo glory in ſuch things, and yet are deeply in the ſpirit of the world, even as by that deſcription of the overcomer of the world, here given by <hi>Iohn;</hi> the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſo called, are evidenced to them, that judgement carnally by outward appearance (as moſt do, which makes them have ſo many Proſelites) but by the ſpirituall eye of faith, however they boſt themſelves as perfect, and vaunt themſelves as out of, and overcomers of the world; yet they are moſt deeply and dangerouſly, though moſt myſtically, and to the world-ward indiſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably overcome of the world, and the ſpirit of the world; as being moſt out of, and reprobate concerning the faith that overcomes the world, <hi>viz.</hi> That Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God, they accounting his coming in the fleſh (as <hi>Rich. Hubberthorne</hi> ſeconded by G. W.) to be but a figure, and touching his being in heaven and work there, and coming thence, being moſt dangerouſly corrupt and unbelievers; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their rejoycing and glorying not in that perſon of Jeſus and his ſufferings and ſacrifice according to the Scripture; as their book, in anſwer to us, and their writings generally evidence, but in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their ſinleſneſſe pretended, and in their actings and ſufferings, by which it is evident that they are not born of God, nor have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world whatever outſideappearances they walke and glory in. 2. Becauſe I produced according to <hi>Johns</hi> teſtimony without diſtinction or alteration, and meant it only of true believing. 3. He ſaies it's true of true believers; as if he would imply that <hi>Paul</hi> and the other holy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110700:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>men, when they ſaid they had ſin in them, were not true believers, though in ſome other falſe ſenſe believes that Jeſus is the Chriſt; what, were the Apoſtles hypocrites when they ſaid they had ſin in them; that <hi>George</hi> thinks them not then to have been true believers? For if they were not true believers, they were feigned believers; and we may well bear G. W.'s railing language of us, and his judging us to be hypocrites, if he judged the Apoſtles, when Apoſtles, were ſuch, ſure G. W. did better before, when he waved it, and fled before the power of God in it, than to rake up ſuch an evaſion, as implies his taxing the Apoſtles to be no true believers when they confeſſed their ſins; or that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad not overcome the world, when they were tranſlated out of it, into Chriſt, and held forth the faith of Chriſt againſt all oppoſitions of the World; then he is guilty of falſehood, in ſaying <hi>John</hi> deſcribes the true believers to be from under the bondage of corruption, when he makes no mention of the bondage of corruption, though that they are ſo in ſome ſenſe is true; but then he ſaies falſe, and belies me in ſaying, that I own not ſuch while men are here, for in ſuch a ſenſe, as true believers are free from the bondage of corruption, that is, from being detained under the guilt of ſin and condemnation for it, or the dominion of it, ſo as to inſlave them to it; I own believers, though not from the being of it in their members, is it all one to have corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a man, yea, and in many things to offend, and to be under the bondage of corruption? Was <hi>James</hi> under the bondage of corruption, as corruption ſignifies ſin, when he ſaid, in many things we offended all; or <hi>John,</hi> when he ſaid, If we ſay we have no ſin we deceive our ſelves, &amp;c. Surely G. W. had need to goe to ſchool to learn more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding before he be a teacher, that cannot diſtinguiſh things that ſo broadly differ. He ſaies, <hi>A man muſt believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, and believe in him too, before he be born of God, as Chriſt ſaid believed in the light, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ye may be the children of the light.</hi> What is this but to fight againſt the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> and to tell him, Nay <hi>John</hi> thou ſaiſt not truly in ſaying, who ever believes that Jeſus is the Chriſt is born of God. Men may believe that and yet not be born of God, for that goes before a mans being born of God, and yet ſome things are before others in order of nature, that yet are not without them; as he that hath life hath breath, &amp; yet, in order of nature, life is before breath: &amp; ſo though it be true, that men muſt believe in the light, that they may be the children of the light; yet, it followes not, that ſome do believe in it that are not the children of it, and yet even they that are born of God, and ſo are children of the light, may be further born of it, and ſo more the children of God; that is, like unto God, as the Diſciples when born of God (for God was their Father) yet Chriſt bids them to love their enemies, &amp;c. That they might be the children of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.44, 45. And yet again, There is ſome difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween believing in the light, and believing Jeſus to be the Chriſt, ſome did believe in the light, before they believed that Jeſus is the Chriſt as <hi>Nathaniel</hi> and <hi>Cornelius</hi> and divers others. So that here is nothing in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110700:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Geo.</hi> yet, but deceit, and oppoſition to the Scripture ſayings, nay, G is broadly contradictory to <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, and ſticks not to make him a lyer, plainly afterward, as well as ſafely to perſwade people that ſome of his party perceived my deceit. For ſaith he, <hi>What people are there of any underſtanding, even among thoſe Prieſts, which this Prieſt</hi> Horne <hi>calls greedy dogs, ſtrong to appetite, that doe not believe that Jeſus is the Christ? Are they therefore born of God?</hi>] What is this but to caſt the lye upon <hi>John,</hi> for being ſo raſh as to ſay, whoſoever believeth Jeſus is the Chriſt, is born of God, when as he ſaies, ſuch as he reviles as the worſt of men, do that, and yet are not born of God? Judge Reader, Whom ſhall we here believe? the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> or <hi>Geo. Whitehead?</hi> Is it not better and truer to ſay, what ever men perſwade themſelves of, and what ever they pretend, they do not believe Jeſus to be the Chriſt, that are not born of God, than thus raſhly to give the Apoſtle the lye: That <hi>George</hi> fled to another ſhift when beat by that Scripture from his former anſwer, that the Apoſtles were not born of God while they confeſſed ſin, he denies not; but indeavours to juſtifie here, what he therein ſaid. For he ſaies here again, that <hi>The Apoſtle condeſcended to the Romans to ſeveral ſtates which be paſſed through, and which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his own, when he writ to them.</hi> Which is not to the purpoſe, For when he writes to the Romans of the ſtates, he had paſſed through, he writes of them as things paſt, not as preſent, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. When we were enemies he reconſiled us; he ſaies not, we are yet enemies, ſo <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.9. I was alive without the Law, but when the Law came, ſin revived and I dyed; and ſo in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Who was before a blaſphemer and a Perſecutor and injurious; we never find him when he was an Apoſtle, to ſay, I am a blaſphemer, &amp;c. But of ſin being in him, he writes in the preſent time; I know that in me, that is, in my fleſh, there dwells no good thing, and I am carnal, ſold under ſin, (not, I ſell my ſelf to ſin as <hi>Ahab,</hi> but am ſold as by an other, with reference to what was done to him in <hi>Adam,</hi> and yet remained upon him, as to the fleſh,) and that he ſpake of himſelf too, and not of others excluding himſelf, is evident, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. So then I my ſelfe (marke he ſaies I my ſelf) with my mind ſerve (he ſaies not did ſerve) the Law of God, but with my fleſh the Law of ſin. Should we ſay, we our ſelves do what we only mean others do, he and his fellowes would call us lyers, and yet he fears not to faſten ſuch an imputation in effect upon the Apoſtles, one after another.</p>
            <p>He would confirme his former ſaying from <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19. which is to as little purpoſe, as if he had quoted <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. For the Apoſtle there ſpeaks nothing of himſelf, or of any ſtate that he ſaies he was then in, as mentioning his own perſon, but ſpeaking of ſpiritual things under earthly metaphors (as of Maſters and Servants, and freedom from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude) He ſaies, <hi>I ſpeak after the manner of men, becauſe of the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of your fleſh.</hi> But is this the manner of men, to ſpeak untruths of them ſelves, as to ſay, they are in that ſtate they are not, to make their ſpeech
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110700:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>more underſtandable, or doth the Apoſtle ſpeak any thing ſounding to that ſenſe there? He ſaies not there, I yeeld my members ſervants to uncleanneſſe; but as ye have (in time paſt) yielded your members ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to uncleanneſſe, &amp;c. ſo yeeld your members now ſervants of righteouſneſſe. Was it not as underſtandable, for the Apoſtle to have ſaid, I did ſometime find a Law in my members, but now I have got rid of it, and there is no ſin in me, as if it had been ſo as to ſay, I do ſee a law in my members? yea, might not this more encourage them to ſin than that, if it be as G. W. often caſts upon us a pleading for ſin, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that ſin is in the Saints? It clearly appears in all this ſtill, that G.W. is much out of the way, and the truth is, neither in, nor with him; for where it could diſtinguiſh between <hi>Paul,</hi> as after the fleſh, and as after the ſpirit in the ſame time, in his fleſh in bondage, and in his mind free, and waiting for the deliverance of his body too in due time, both from ſins and ſufferings: But how can he diſtinguiſh ſuch things, that could not diſtinguiſh things nearer hand? But whereas I ſaid, I was able in the ſtrength of God to worry ſuch Foxes as he, that is to baſſle and confound them, as I alſo actually was helpt to do, yet becauſe I ſay, after that people ſee I was weary and ſpent, he vapors as if I was not therefore in the ſtrength of God, forgeting that of the Apoſtle, that at the ſame time in different reſpects, a man may be ſtrong and weak both; when I am weak, then am I ſtrong; and, I was among you in weakeneſſe, yet my ſpeech was in the demonſtration of the ſpirit and power, 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 2.3, 4. Surely when I ſaid I was able to worry him, in the ſtrength of the Lord, I did not ſay, or ſignifie, nor could any of the people I ſuppoſe ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend me, that I was able to beat him at handicuffs, or had ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Lungs then he, but that I was able, by the power of the truth, to make manifeſt his deceits: which alſo God gave me bodyly ſtrength to do, ſo as to the ſatisfaction of the indifferent auditory, and had I nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded more to that, I queſtion not but he would have given it me: He that cannot diſtinguiſh ſpiritual ſtrength from bodily, how ſhould he diſtinguiſh between <hi>Pauls</hi> ſtate after the ſpirit, and his ſtate at the ſame time after the fleſh? As a man in the fleſh, warring yet againſt ſin, and wiſhing for deliverance (for that's the force of that phraſe (who will deliver?) as <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29. according to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> who will give them an heart to fear me? argues not that the Lord was ignorant, or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who would, but an earneſt deſire that they had ſuch an heart) but in the ſame time he thanked God by Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24, 25. and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> was free in his ſpirit and more than a conqueror in all his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, though Chriſt who dwelt in his heart by faith (though I never read what G. W. intimates that Chriſt was in <hi>Pauls</hi> fleſh, though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and therethrough he might manifeſt his power and vertues) but us to his body that was not above priſon and weakneſſe and death, even ſo, neither was his fleſh free from ſin being in it, though his ſpirit was ſet free and above it.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110700:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>made himſelfe a ſervant to all, that he might gain the more, and became a Jew to the Jew, and weak to the weak.</hi> True, in his uſe of indifferent things, ſuch as meats, drinks, wages, &amp;c. But he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came not a Jew to the Jew, in not believing or confeſſing Jeſus to be the Chriſt, and though to thoſe that being weak in the Faith, doubted of their liberty to ſome ſuch outward things as before mentioned; he alſo abſtained from the uſe of his freedome to them, not telling them of his liberty, leſt he ſhould offend them; but in thoſe things having his faith to himſelfe, as if he alſo was weake, as he adviſes others, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.28, 29. Yet it's evident that was not the caſe here. For to what purpoſe ſhould he pretend, in ſome places to be in ſuch ſtates, &amp; in other places of the ſame Epiſtle, to the ſame people, expreſs himſelf to be far above ſuch ſtates, as G.W. ſaies he did, in ſaying, he was at peace with God, &amp;c. So that theſe appear (as indeed they are) ſilly ſhifts of G. W. to hide the nakedneſſe of his aſſertion and corruption of his judgement, but they will not do it. As for his perſonal accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of us, as uncivil, and bawling and wrangling, and deſiring to tie him up to <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> they are vain and falſe accuſations, and ſo I ſhall paſſe them; As alſo his after inſinuations of rantings, and loves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and of a woman ſet up for a Teacher by us (when of any woman ſet up to teach by us, I know none: who turned Ranters is known so be ſome of their luſts, &amp;c.) as alſo his charging me, as ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>G. Roſe</hi> as a diſtracted man, and yet bringing his words againſt them, when as I ſaid but, that the people heard him begin at a diſtance like a kind of diſtracted man, to call out, not that I counted him a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted man; theſe perſonal and untrue reflections, I ſay I paſſe as impertinencies. And as for his ſaying, <hi>We would not ſuffer him to read in our Book, and yet we read out of theirs,</hi> and his vain and falſe inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations therefrom, the ridiculouſneſſe thereof is ſufficiently cleared in the relation of our diſcourſe, though he take no more notice of it, than if no ſuch thing had been mentioned. His asking queſtions, when he ſhould have anſwered, were meer diviations from our buſineſſe; and yet I know of none that I anſwered not then, except that [what death came in by ſin] which he ſought in ſubtilty, as I conceived, to put me upon, that he might wind out from the thing that puzled him. As for <hi>his feeling the power of God over us</hi>] He might feel it over us indeed, to protect us, and inable us to baffle him, for which we bleſſe the Lord, but otherwiſe it appeared not with him, in his anſwers, nor yet appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with him, in what he hath written in his own vindication. He ſaies, <hi>The Apoſtles wept with them that wept, and waite for the Redemption of the body where it was not redeemed; as he travelled for the Gallatians, &amp;c.</hi> Which are nothing to the purpoſe, for a man may weep with thoſe that weep, without ſaying falſly, that he is exerciſed with the ſame trials in himſelfe, and of his own, as others weep under: Cannot I weep with ſuch as weep for the abſence of Gods ſpirit from them, or for the loſſe of ſome neer relation, unleſſe I ſay, I am in the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110700:13"/>with them. Nay, if I ſay its ſo with me, as with them, then do I not ſhew ſuch charity to them; for then it may rather be judged, that I weep for my own afflictions, than with them for theirs, one ſaying of the Apoſtle any where, that his body was already redeemed from that bondage, the redemption of it from which he there ſaies, he waited for, were more then and hundred ſuch ſhifts, his proofs alleadged in our diſcourſe, from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. He was then ſo anſwered to, and beaten from that, he hath here paſſed them over, as not able to relieve him. For the Apoſtles travelling for the <hi>Galatians;</hi> as I remember in the diſpute, he diſclaimed it then, for making for his purpoſe when T. M. was anſwering him to it, thinking he had had ſome reference to it, in what he ſpake about <hi>Pauls</hi> travelling, and that, its not to his purpoſe is evident, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaies not there, as in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that he waited or travelled for the redemption of his own body, no, nor for the redemption of their bodies, but till Chriſt was formed in them, not coupling in himſelfe together with them as condeſcending in ſuch a manner to their ſtates.</p>
            <p>Setting down two or three of my queſtions, together without his anſwer to them, he then taxes me for omitting the word (bondage) in ſpeaking of the redemption of the body, which word he ſaies he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, a great matter, is it not, when as the very word redemption implies ſome bondage to be redeemed from, nor doth the Apoſtle uſe the word, Bondage, in ſpeaking of the redemption of their body, the creatures groaning to be delivered, and the Saints waiting for the redemption of the body we before ſhewed (at the diſpute alſo) to be diſtinct things and not the ſame.</p>
            <p>He ſaies here again, <hi>That the Saints had that redemption of the body from the bondage of corruption, when the creatures were delivered into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberty of the Sons of God before their deceaſe.</hi> But he proves it not, nor could do at the diſpute; 'tis proofs we looke for, and not bare aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon his own authority, which without proof from Scriptures, weighs with us nothing. The Scripture neither ſaies, that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had the deliverance into the liberty of the Sons of God, nor that the Saints had the redemption of their body before their deceaſe, but ſpeaks of both as things future, and therefore groaned and waited for, ſee elſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19, 20, 21, 22, 23. And indeed they could not be before thoſe Saints deceaſed, for evident it is that the Apoſtle (<hi>ver.</hi> 17.18.) ſpeaks about their ſufferings with Chriſt, and reigning with Chriſt, and ſpeaks of the ſufferings with him; as firſt, and the Reigne, as a thing afterward; the ſufferings are of this preſent time, or life, but the glory is to be after revealed, and therefore ſpoken of as in the future, to this preſent time, [ſhall be revealed in or upon us] and about that glory and revelation of it, and the redemption of the body from the ſufferings that go before it ſpeaks, <hi>ver.</hi> 19, 20, 21, 22, 23. Now ſeeing the glory could not be revealed nor the redemption of the body (from the ſufferings) be before the ſufferings be accompliſhed, and their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110700:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſufferings (even the ſufferings of the preſent time) were to bodily Death, therefore it followes, that the redemption of the body from the bondage it was under, in, and by thoſe ſufferings could not be till after their deceaſe, except the Redemption be before the bondage, and the glory thereof before the ſufferings, contrary to the Apoſtles order, in ſpeaking of them; which one conſideration to thoſe that can and will ſee, may ſuffice to ſhew, that it's no error or abſurdity in me (as G. W. after reckons it) to ſay, that the corruption which <hi>Paul</hi> wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and groaned for, the Redemption of his body from, is the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mortality (in part) though he hath belyed me, by his addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in ſaying, as part of my aſſertion [in which the body is in death, when it is in corruption] for I had no ſuch non-ſenſical expreſſion.</p>
            <p>That the Apoſtles waited for the Redemption of the body from all the bondage and miſery that the ſufferings of this time, or life could bring it to, and ſo from bondage to death and grave alſo, and in that hope and expectation, yeilded up their bodies to ſufferings for Chriſts ſake, is evident in the Scriptures. It was the hope of the Reſurrection even of that reſurrection of the dead, in which, what is ſown in Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is raiſed in Incorruption, that led them into Jeoperdies, &amp; to fight with Beaſts after the manner of men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.30, 32, 42, 53. &amp; that made them ſpeak, though death therethrough wrought in them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12, 13, 14. Oh how wicked and corrupt concerning the faith, are theſe men that deride the looking for, and hope of that Redemption of the body, becauſe a thing ſo many hundreds of yeares off! as if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo far off, therefore they did not look for it: Whenas the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that died in the Faith, and received not, as then, the promiſes, lived many hundred years before the Apoſtles, and yet they ſaw theſe promiſes a far off, and imbraced them, and confeſſed themſelves ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Pilgrims in hope and expectation of a City and Country pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13, 14, 15, 39, 40.</note> in the receit of which they ſhall not be perfect without us believers of theſe laſt ages. Now what they hoped for they waited for too; <hi>For if we hope for what we ſee not, then do we with expectation wait for it,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, Rom. 8.24, 25. And if they (the Fathers) hoped and waited, and yet wait, for the Redemption of their body in the reſurrection of it, might not the Apoſtles much more, to whom it was by many hundreds of years nearer? or is it more abſurd to ſay <hi>Paul</hi> hath not yet the Redemption of the body for which he waited, then that <hi>Abraham</hi> hath not yet received all the promiſes for which he hoped? or that either of their bodies are not yet raiſed, nor that glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Chriſt yet come, in which they are to be raiſed? Their expectation of which, while here, led them to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14. But it appears plainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> G. W's. deriding ſuch an expectation, that he expects and waits for, nor groans after no ſuch thing, whatſoever he ſubtilly ſay after that, <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 14, 16. of 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. he never denyed nor doubted of, and ſo ſlighted diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110700:14"/>about it, no, no, he was not willing to open his corrupt ſenſe too broadly about them, as may after appear.</p>
            <p>He ſaies, <hi>Paul groaned not to be uncloathed, but cloathed upon;</hi> True, it was not death he groaned for, but to be clothed upon with his houſe from heaven, which becauſe they knew they could not be clothed with, till the earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, therefore they were willing rather to be abſent from the body, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. But if <hi>Paul,</hi> when he wrote that Epiſtle, groaned for that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the body, which he ſaies he groaned for when he writ to the <hi>Romans,</hi> (as G.W. alſo implies, by his quoting that place to parallel the other, as indeed it doth) then why did G. W. at the diſpute endeavour to prove, that the Apoſtle had that Redemption of the body when he writ this Epiſtle, becauſe he ſaies therein, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.8. he could do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth? Thinks he, that <hi>Paul</hi> received that Redemption of the body, between his writing, what is in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. and what is writ in <hi>Chap.</hi> 13? Surely ſuch a charge would have made him ſome where, in the very writing, break forth into an extraordinary Tryumph, more than we find him therein, between the ſaid paſſages to do. Indeed <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. he tels us, of being taken up into Paradiſe, and of abundance of Revelations, but whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the body, or not, he knew not; and beſides, he ſpeakes of things above 14 yeares before, and ſure he was not ſo long writing that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or did G. W. rather wittingly, bring that ſaying, to blind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive people? That appears moſt likely, and ſo that he is a Deceiver indeed, and to be therefore counted accurſed. 'Its true, <hi>too that</hi> Paul <hi>calls that Redemption of the body, the Adoption, and Chriſt was made under the Law, to Redeem thoſe that were under the Law, that they might receive the Adoption of Sons;</hi>] and that Adoption the Apoſtle had received in his ſpirit, when he ſaid he waited for the Adoption, the Redemption of he body, for in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 16. he ſaies, even of them he wrote to (and therefore their ſtate was not a ſtate below being Sons of God, and ſo born of God) <hi>Ye have received the Spirit of Adoption, whereby we cry abba Father, and the ſpirit it ſelf beareth witneſſe with our ſpirits, that we are the children of God.</hi> And therefore ſurely born of God, though yet they waited for that Adoption, the Redemption of the body, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. So that ſtill the more G. ſtrugles, the more he is proved a deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and my charge appears made good againſt him, and no ly for me to ſay ſo. Nor need to prove, that the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them, and were ſinners ſo long as they lived (though that alſo was done from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. as before) it's enough that they confeſſe ſin in them, and waited for the Redemption of the body, after they were born of God, which was the thing that G. denyed. Nor need I prove that the <hi>Quakers</hi> preach themſelves free from ſin, ſeeing they grant (or deny not) that charge againſt them in their anſwer to our firſt Book. Nor will their having confeſſed their ſins ſerve the turne, as was ſhewed at the beginning; though yet G. W. is here covering
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110700:14"/>and pleading for his ſins or errors, as it is apparent, ſo the Apoſtles did not, much leſſe need we, prove that they, <hi>preach themſelves perfect, as if their preaching made them perfect</hi>] for no body ever charged them with ſuch a thing in that ſenſe. It's enough, that they preach them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſo perfect, as that they have no ſin, for which they need Chriſt to be their Propitiation.</p>
            <p>See again Reader, how <hi>George</hi> is put to his ſhifts about <hi>Aſa. 'Tis not ſaid</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that his heart was perfect all his life-time</hi>] as if all his daies (to wit, of his reigne) did not laſt to the end of his life, had he a life time after all his daies were ended? If he lived ſome daies after his heart ceaſed to be perfect, then was not his heart perfect all his daies, and then the Scripture ſaith not truly, ſhall we believe the Scriptures or G. W's, gloſſe? <hi>That his heart was perfect all the while be did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, and while the Land was quiet under his reigne, but not after.</hi> That is a gloſſe of his own brain, againſt the authority of the Text, ſeeing that time was not all his daies, nor is it ſaid, his worke was perfect all his daies, but his heart; and that might be perfect, as to his owning no god but the true God, and deſiring to approve it ſelfe to him, notwithſtanding ſome raſh paſſions, and neglect in ſeeking to him for a time, as well as it is ſaid to have been perfect, notwithſtanding the high places were not removed, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.14. As ſome Kings whoſe works were perfecter did, &amp; as he alſo ſhould have done, had his works been perfect and ſinleſſe. But wee ſee, both by what he ſaies to this and other Scriptures before mentioned, <hi>George</hi> makes no great matter of juſtling his authority with the authority of the Scriptures, which evidences him to be a dangerous fellow, not to be liſtened to. View we his endeavours, to vindicate his corrupt ſayings about the coming of Chriſt, mentioned, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16. to which coming they ſaid in their Book, the Saints that were then alive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained. He ſaies, <hi>I wreſted their words, and made a falſe conſtruction of them, contrary to the end and intent of them, for what they ſaid</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>was againſt our imaginations, who look</hi> (he ſaies) <hi>carnally for the coming of Chriſt, as many of the World do, of whom Chriſt ſaid, I go away and the world ſeeth me no more.</hi> John 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That I wreſted not his words, let their words and mine, being compared, witneſſe; They ſaid, as for that, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15. (our quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they anſwered to, was 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16. concerning the coming of the Lord from heaven (which phraſe is <hi>v.</hi> 16. not the 15th. though they both ſpeak of the ſame coming) that coming of Chriſt the Saints that were then alive remained to it. Now from that I inferred, that if they remained to that coming, wherein they that are found alive, ſhall not prevent them that ſleep, then they remained to that coming, in which the dead in Chriſt (even the dead bodies of the Saints that ſleep in ſuch ſence as it's ſaid, that <hi>Stephen</hi> fell aſleep when he dyed, ſhall be raiſed, and the living changed, &amp;c. Now let the Reader, read 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15.16. and ſee if that doth not neceſſarily follow; and whither that be not the coming of the Lord there ſpoken to, to which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110700:15"/>that phraſe [we that live and remain] is coupled, in verſe 15, 16, and 17. So that if the Apoſtles and Saints then living, did remain to the coming of Chriſt from Heaven there ſpoken of, (as they ſaid) then did they remain till his coming with a ſhout, and the voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, and the dead in Chriſt being raiſed, as is evident; And I did not wreſt their words beſides the drift of them, only they meant not indeed, that they lived to the Reſurrection of the dead bodies of the Saints (though of that the Apoſtle there ſpeaks) becauſe they believe no ſuch thing, but undermine it as I charged them. <hi>That we carnaly looke for the coming of Chriſt, as many of the world do</hi>] is not only their reproof of us, but an intimate blaſpheming of the truth, for we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed no other looking for the coming of Chriſt from Heaven, but that ſpoken to in 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.21. which here they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach as an imagination of ours, as earnally looking for him; as if it was but a carnal imagination, to think that Chriſt ſhall ever ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, and come in like manner from heaven, as the Diſciples ſee him go up into heaven, that is, viſibly and bodily, by which reproach they are more made manifeſt to be Deceivers, and ſuch as ought to be accounted accurſed by us, as underminers of the hope of the Goſpel, nor doth Chriſt ſay in <hi>John</hi> 14. as G. ſecretly implies, that the world ſhall ſee him no more, he ſhall come no more viſibly to them, but the world (after a little while) ſeeth me no more, or not yet (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) it is in the preſent time, ſeeth me not yet, or no more, becauſe he is now only to be ſeen in the ſpirit by faith, whilſt he is in bodily a b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the world hath not that faith by which to ſee him.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>He vindicated thoſe words of theirs, and witneſſed to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral comings of Chriſt, as he was revealed to the Saints, from glory, to glory</hi>] How he vindicated their words, both the relation of our diſcourſe (which he confirmes herein to be true, and that he had no cauſe to fault me, for ſaying his anſwers were to that purpoſe, as I have related them (which I added becauſe I did not pretend to, nor could I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late every word of his anſwer, with all the circumſtances, tautologies and circumlocutions of them) for to the ſame purpoſe as he here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes I related) and what he ſaith here ſhews: unleſſe by (vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their words) he mean (as a diſtinct thing, from witneſſing to the ſeveral comings of Chriſt, as he was revealed to the Saints, &amp;c.) what he alledged from the next Chapter about ſleeping, and from <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.25. about the dead hearing the voice of the Son of God, and from 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. Of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> waiting from the coming of Chriſt from Heaven; and then alſo, he both confirmes my relation, that mentions thoſe anſwers, before his talking of the ſeveral degrees of Chriſts revealing himſelf to the Saints, and ſo that he falfly cavils af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, when he ſaies, that, <hi>in pag.</hi> 11. <hi>I lay down many words that he never ſpake</hi>] for there are not many words of his laid down in that <hi>page,</hi> as the Reader thereof may ſee, and what is laid down as his, I dare call God, and the Auditory to witneſſe I have not wronged him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110700:15"/>in, yea and he himſelf in this anſwer, acknowledges divers of them, and alſo how ſorrily he vindicated their words, or rather how groſly he prevaricated inſtead of vindicating them, alledging the ſleeping in ſecurity, againſt which the Apoſtle warnes them, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.6. as an interpretation of the ſleeping in Jeſus, about which in, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13, 14, 15. he comforts them; and the raiſing the dead in ſins, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.25. as anſwering to the riſing of the dead in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 16. and the coming of Chriſt from Heaven, which the believing <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> that had turned from dumb Idols waited for, as all one with that efficacy of the voice of Chriſt, cauſing the dead in ſins to hear, and hearing, to live, ſpoken of <hi>John</hi> 5.25. Such a vindication of their words, was but a more evident manifeſtation of their ignorance and corruption.</p>
            <p>He adds, that he, <hi>Never denyed the coming of the Lord from Heaven, when he ſhall bring with him, them that ſleep in Jeſus, and raiſe the dead in Chriſt, nor ever ſaid, that that was already over and past.</hi> As he ſaies <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed him.</hi> That he in ſo many expreſſe words, denyed the coming of Chriſt from Heaven, when he ſhall bring with him them that ſleep, I never charged him; nor did he ever confeſſe that coming, &amp; that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him them that ſleep in him, and raiſing the dead in Chriſt, the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of, but undermines it, while he ſaies, that the Saints then alive remained to it: And calls our expecting it, but an Imagination of ours, and a carnal looking for him, yea, and though he did not in expreſſe words directly ſay it is over and paſt, yet his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Saints then alive (namely when the Apoſtle ſo wrote) remained to it, clearly implies it, for is not remained a word of the time paſt, he ſaid not, they do or ſhall remain to it, but remained in the time paſt and over. Thinks he we cannot underſtand words, when we hear them? But he intimates his crafty meaning, in ſaying he never ſaid, that was already over and paſt, a few line, after. When he ſaies, <hi>What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion would I charge upon them</hi> (and is that a ſtrange thing to find them in confuſion) <hi>as to ſay, the coming of Chriſt, at which, the dead in him are to be raiſed, is already paſt and over, as if that which is yet to be, is over and paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See here, the ſence in which G. W. never ſaid, that coming of Chriſt, is over and paſt, not that that coming of Chriſt there ſpoken of, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16. Is over and paſt to the Apoſtles and Saints of that age; To them Chriſt came, and the dead in him were raiſed, and they, the then living Saints, were changed, and all caught up together to meete him in the ayre; This G. denies not to be their meaning; nay he implies it to be their mind, in his next words. <hi>viz. That with that non-ſence I might as well have charged the Saints as them,</hi> who <hi>remained,</hi> unto the coming of the Lord, and yet did not prevent them, which were aſleep from being raiſed, in which (beſides other corruptions, which I may by and by mention) he aſſerts that thoſe Saints, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to that coming of the Lord, mentioned, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 17. thats
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110700:16"/>not the thing he ever ſaid was over and paſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That coming of the Lord to thoſe Saints; but in this ſence, he never ſaid it, <hi>viz.</hi> That as it is to come yet, or yet to be (as he implies the ſame, or like coming is to ſome in theſe and following ages) ſo he never ſaid it was over and paſt, for that's nonſence, to ſay, what ſhall be, is paſt. Minde then Reader, what corruption of mind he here implies, namely that, that coming of Chriſt there ſpoken of, is not to be, to all dead and living Saints at once, even to all that dyed and lived in their ſeveral ages, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with thoſe of us (that is, of the body of believers, all which, in all ages, the Apoſtle ſpeaks there of, as of one ſociety or body, as in mine anſwers I cleared, that to be the ſence of the Apoſtles) that ſhall then be found living, and remaining to it; But that that coming of Chriſt was to the Saints in that age, and is to the Saints in every age; but if ſo, then I would know what Saints did not live and remain to that coming, if he come to the Saints in every age, do any Saints dye before he come, and not remain to it, as the Apoſtle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies diſtinguiſhing the living and remaining, from them that ſleep and are dead in Chriſt? If ſome dyed before his coming to the living, did thoſe dead Saints riſe at his coming to thoſe living ones in every age? If ſo, then they make a Reſurrection of the dead, even the dead in body, in every age, or continually, and yet that which was corruptable in them, never puts on incorruption, but lies and Rots, for their corruptable bodies lye yet in their Sepulchres, as it's ſaid of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> after many generations. But if the dead Saints riſe not again, in every age when Chriſt comes to the living, then how do not the living Saints prevent thoſe that are aſleep? Why, for that G. W. finds out a new deviſe to ſalve that matter, while he ads of his own head, they prevent them not from riſing, but thoſe words (from riſing) are his own, not in the Text, nor doth the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>prevent</hi>) ſignifie ſuch a thing there, as to hinder or keep from a thing, as G.W. ignorantly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies; but the ſence is, we ſhal not be before them. The living Saints ſhal not be in their glory before thoſe, which are dead, even as to their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ſo the word <hi>(prevent)</hi> that comes of <hi>prevenire,</hi> ſignifies in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.13. and 119, 147, 148. and elſe where.</p>
            <p>He ſaies, <hi>When he urged the Apostles remaining till the coming of the Lord, as in</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.15, 17. <hi>I to render him edious</hi> (nay to diſcover his deceits) <hi>urged,</hi> ver. 13, 14, 16. <hi>which he ſaies, he never denyed, nor doubted of her.</hi> And ſo he ſlighted diſputing about it, though I would make it diſputable, as if all thoſe verſes ſpake not of the ſame coming of Chriſt; or as if the word, <hi>then,</hi> (then we which are alive, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.) did not clearly pelate to the coming with a ſhout, and the dead in Chriſt riſing, ſpoken of in <hi>ver.</hi> 16. And as if he ſlighted and waved diſputing about thoſe verſes, and yet mentioned the ſleeping ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.6. and the dead living by the voice of Chriſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.25. With evident reference to what I urged from <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 14, 15. where thoſe phraſes of ſleeping, and dead in Chriſt are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110700:16"/>thus we ſee Foxes have their holes to creep into when perſued by the truth; but theſe do but ſlenderly hide his deceit. He grants, his mention of <hi>John</hi> 5.25. touching the dead hearing the voice of the Son of God, and what occaſion had he to mention that, if he ſlighted diſputing about the 16. verſe, where the dead being raiſed, is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? He ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h a ſtarting hole, ſuch as it is, for that too; For he ſaies, <hi>That theſe that were dead, or aſleep, in their ſins, might come to be raiſed out of them, and live.</hi> This he ſaies, <hi>He knew was the moſt needful for many people that heard us, to know, they having ſuch as I for their Teachers, whoſe Miniſtry</hi> (he ſlanderouſly ſaith) <hi>doth greatly tend to keep men in their ſins, when we ſo much ſtrive for ſin, in contending and pleading for it, as I have done.</hi> Ah ſhameful ſubterfuge! canſt thou not ſmell a Fox hear, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? Hiſtorians ſay, when they are cloſly perſued, they fling about their piſſe with their tailes to annoy their perſuers with its ſtench, and ſo doth G. W. here; For is it likely he would run from vindicating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt my charge, and clearing himſelf of the guilt of it (which had been the beſt courſe to bring people off from liſtening to my Miniſtry, and to have attended to theirs, in which he ſuppoſes the voice of Chriſt may be better met with to raiſe them from their ſins) to mention a Scripture as paralleling the riſing of the dead in Chriſt, which is quite to another purpoſe, and ſo to give me advantage againſt him, to make all the people ſee his weakneſſe and impertinency, and inability to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf againſt my charge? Was his bare mentioning that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and waving it againe, when I ſhewed its impertenency, that way to raiſe them out of their ſins, that were a ſleep in them? Or was that the voice of the Son of man, that the dead hear? Oh ſorry man and hard put to it, that is forced to deviſe ſuch ſorry ſhifts to hide himſelfe in! and what would he do if he had not that ſlander at his tongues end (that we plead for ſin, and that our Miniſtry tends to keep people in it) which reflects upon the Apoſtles equally with us, as I have before ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</p>
            <p>Surely a great part of his Books are uſually made up with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating of that ſenſleſſe reproach. For ſurely our Preaching the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Reſurrection and the judgement to come, more directly tend to awake people out of ſins; yea, our telling them that they have ſin in them to watch againſt, then their corrupt denyals and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minings of thoſe doctrines do. Thus I have further made good my charge in vindicating my mannagement of it from his cavils therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, in the main things objected by him. The reſt are more trivial, and a ſhorter touch will ſerve to overthrough them, as his chargeing me with, <hi>A diſſembling imitation, in ſaying I appealed to that of God, in all the people when he ſaies, I deny that all have the light of Chriſt in them, which is that of God they ſpeak of, and appeal to in all.</hi> How filly is this, For had we all men before us to ſpeak to? Or if the light of Chriſt was in all them, follows it, that it is in all the infants and Reprobates in the world? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, when they appeal to that of God in all, they mean it, of the light
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110700:17"/>of Chriſt (namely his ſpiritual light, which only I deny to be in all at all times) followes it that I muſt do ſo to; Is there nothing of God in men beſides that ſpiritual light? Is not the ſoul, the underſtanding faculty, and the reaſon, of God? and is that the light of Chriſt, they ſpeak of, as brought forth in ſome to be the Prince of peace? So his taxing, <hi>My laughing at them, as not miniſtring grace to the people, but ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up folly and madneſſe.</hi> What? coth not the laughing of the juſt to ſee their enemies defeated, as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 52.6. miniſter grace to the hearers? might not my expreſſing my joy in the Lord, for his goodneſſe in ſtrengthning and helping me againſt ſuch a Bravado, that brag of what they were and could do, provoke the people to ſeek to know the truth of, and truſt in that God whom they ſee after ſolemn appeals to him, before them, and deſire to manifeſt his truth, and ſtop the mouth of error, ſo to baffle him by his poor weak ſervant? Surely it might.</p>
            <p>Whereas I ſaid, and proved from <hi>Col,</hi> 2.10. with 3, 5, 8. That men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in Chriſt, may yet have ſins in themſelves to mortifie, he turns &amp; perverts my ſaying ſhamefully, when he ſaies, <hi>The Apoſtle ſaid not thoſe that were in fornication and uncleanneſſe, &amp;c. were compleat in Chriſt, for thoſe that were compleat in Christ had put off all theſe</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nor ſaid I, thoſe that are in fornication and uncleanneſſe are compleat in Chriſt. Is G. ſo ſimple as not to diſcerne a large diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, between ſins being in men, and men being in thoſe ſins! as much as between mens having unclean humors, as of blood or excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in them, and their being in uncleanneſſe by the iſſuing of them upon them, as was noted before. I ſaid not men that are in thoſe evils, but that have ſuch evils in them to mortifie, may yet be compleat in Chriſt, and that the Scripture above quoted clearly proves, nor doth that hinder that G. W. alledges. <hi>viz. That thoſe that are compleat in Chriſt have put off thoſe things;</hi> for thoſe that have put them off, are bid to put them off ſtill, See elſe <hi>Col.</hi> 8.3. But now you alſo put off all theſe things, Anger, Wrath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Seeing that you have put off the old man with his deeds. They had put the old man off, and yet are bid to put them off, becauſe they are not perfectly put off at once, ſo as no need of putting them off any more. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. They that are ſaid to be unleavened, are yet bid to purge out the old leaven. As a Wife in taking an Husband yeilds up her ſelfe to be his, and puts off her will, or power over her ſelfe, and yet needs dayly to be exerciſing herſelfe therein to put off and deny her will. <hi>George</hi> ſaies, <hi>The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers could not remain, where the body on which they were, were put off.</hi> Shall we believe <hi>Georges</hi> reaſon, or the Apoſtles ſaying? Sure tis <hi>George's</hi> ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and error that he cannot apprehend (or elſe his worſe minde, to deceive people that he will not own) the things of God. They ſeem fooliſhneſſe to him, that a man may be compleat in Chriſt, and yet have ſins in him to mortifie. And becauſe he cannot comprehend them (and how ſhould he, when he is ſo far out about the faith of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110700:17"/>perſon of Chriſt and believes not in him, but in an internal prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple only in himſelf and others?) he endeavours to render them fooliſhneſſe to others alſo, and ſticks not to oppoſe his ſayings to the Apoſtles, and to invent gloſſes and ſhifts, as if the Apoſtles ſaid not thoſe things to the ſame perſons, but to perſons in different ſtates. And whereas I replyed, did the Apoſtle write one Chapter, to one part of the poople, and another Chapter, to another part of them? He ſaies, <hi>I manifest my blindneſſe, becauſe the Epiſtle was not then divided into Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he manifeſts his cavilling minde in ſo ſaying, For, what if the Epiſtle was not divided by him into Chapters, as I know it was not? there is the leſſe colour for him to ſay, that thoſe things in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.10. according to our now diviſion of it, were writ to people in one State, &amp; thoſe in <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.5, 8. writ to people of another. His own conceit would rather imply that the Apoſtle had ſo divided his Epiſtle into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Chapters, to ſeveral Perſons or ſtates, than my asking him that queſtion upon that blind ſhift of his.</p>
            <p>Would <hi>George</hi> and the <hi>Quakers</hi> inſtead of divers ſtates of divers Perſons, conſider or believe the divers and different reſpects or ſtates of the ſame perſons, they would avoid all this their error and confuſion as to this point, and the controverſy thereabout between us would ceaſe. However, I propound it to the Reader, for thy uſefulneſſe, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That the ſame perſons that believe, are conſiderable, as they are men and women, and have natural beings of Souls and Bodies, as ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Adam</hi> by propagation, and ſo they are ſinful, mortal, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to many infirmities, and have members on earth to mortifie. And yet the ſame perſons as they are, by the grace of God, begotten to know and believe in Chriſt, and are reckoned after him, have another ſtate in him, which is not reckoned after <hi>Adam,</hi> and whatthey are in themſelves; And ſo they are Saints, Holy, Spotleſſe, compleat, &amp; the Apoſtles ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpeaks of the ſame perſons with reference to the one conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſometimes with reference to the other, as men, to keep them lowly and little in their own eyes, and to provoke them to look more diligently to Chriſt, and abide in him, and as in Chriſt to encourage them againſt the diſcouragements from ſelfe and world, and to provoke them to thankfulneſſe to God, and confidence in him, and to abide in him, where it is ſo well with them. So the Apoſtle ſpeaks in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently of himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25. And that one conſideration too ſhews how both <hi>Solomon,</hi> in ſaying there is no man that ſinneth not, and <hi>John</hi> in ſaying he that is born of God ſinneth not, do both ſpeak truly of the ſame perſons with different reſpects. No man living, as he is a man from <hi>Adam,</hi> though a believer, but as ſo conſidered, hath ſin, and ſinneth; that is, doth that that is ſinful, though its not imputed to him that believeth, becauſe his mind being renewed, conſents not to it, but ſtrives (not for it, as theſe men ſay of us) but againſt it: and yet as born of God and according to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110700:18"/>or new man, the man that believeth and abideth in Chriſt, ſins not, nor can ſin, commit or conſent to the ſin that is and remaineth in his fleſh and members, and is there to be put off yet and mortified by him.</p>
            <p>He ſaies, <hi>Many ſaw the truth over me.</hi> Yes over me, as my defence and Protection, I believe they did, and error under my feet. But none that ſaw things rightly, could ſee truth with them, nor what they erroneonſly call truth, damping or confuting me, for then could I not have laughed (as he ſaies) or rejoiced over them. As for what peace they had in the truth, may be conjectured from their want of honeſty and truth in all hitherto diſcovered, and I ſhall not need to grudge them their Peace, but wiſh them more truth, that their peace may be therein, and not in deceit. As for his coming alone into the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that may be; and yet it may be truly ſaid, his friends came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, as the word <hi>with</hi> ſignifies a conſent with him in their coming alſo, even as though Chriſt was buried alone, before the believers now living were born into the world, yet they may be ſaid to be buried with him, as thoſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. My diſcovery of his deceitful abuſe of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1. he wiſely paſſes over; I hope he is aſhamed of it, that he neither at his coming then, or now, hath a word to juſtifie himſelfe therein. <hi>That I would encourage thoſe in power to perſecute him, and to cauſe the outward man to ſuffer,</hi> followes not from my ſaying, that they (namely, thoſe of them amongſt us where he hath been proved a Deceiver) ſhould do well, not to ſuffer him to ſpeak his pretended words from the Lord, except he recant his errors, no more than our Saviour encouraged the Church of <hi>Thyatyra</hi> to perſecute <hi>Jezebel</hi> in reproving the Angel thereof, for ſuffering her to teach, &amp; to ſeduce the people. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20. and in ſuch waies as he ought not to have ſuffered <hi>Jezebel</hi> to teach and ſeduce, in the like way perſons in power hinder G. W. or any that are proved to be deceivers without perſecution of their bodies, except that was perſecution Chriſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; no more doth it follow, that we are ſuch, by our own confeſſion, as have not the Seal of God upon our foreheads, becauſe we ſay they (the <hi>Quakers</hi>) are a heavy judgement of God to us in this Nation, and are like the Locuſts out of the bottomleſſe Pit, for it is not ſaid that the Locuſts were a judgement or tryal, to none that had the Seal of God in their foreheads, but that they ſhould not hurt them. And, I trow, the houſe of God is not hurt by the judgement of God that begins there, nor are we hurt by the <hi>Quakers;</hi> though they be troubleſome, yet by occaſion of that trouble, bleſſed be the Lord we have got good: they being made as means to provoke as to exerciſe our ſelves more to look to God, and by contending for his truth againſt them, to grow more clear and confident therein. As for his boaſts of their borders in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged. See what is ſaid of the falſe Prophets; <hi>many ſhall follow their pernitious waies,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.2. All they in <hi>Aſia</hi> turned away from <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. Thy were never the better for that, not the multitude
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110700:18"/>of followers, but the truth of the Doctrine is to be regarded.</p>
            <p>But above all, Reader, ſee and admire, that a man ſhould be ſo infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated or blinded with malice as this G. W. appears to be, in his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villing againſt the words of the Holy Ghoſt quoted by me, from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63 10. Which he repeats as my words thus. I. H. ſayth, The King Chriſt ſhall rejoice in God, every one that ſweareth by him ſhall glory, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To which he ſaies, <hi>If every one that ſwears by Chriſt ſhall glory, then muſt the drunkards and Lyars and all ſuch prophane perſons as ſwear by him glory:</hi> And ſo this Doctrine, (mark this doctrine) which is the Doctrine of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and only quoted by me, &amp; with an explication of the word <hi>ſwear</hi> too, according to the languag of the new Teſtament, for I ſaid every one that ſweareth or confeſſeth, which he wilfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>ed. <hi>This Doctrine</hi> (ſaies he,) <hi>tends to the encouraging of drunkards, and prophane perſons in ſwearing, which is againſt the doctrine of Chriſt, which is againſt the Oathes and ſwearing which was under the Law, &amp;c.</hi> What may we think of ſuch a pittiful man as this, that ſhames not thus to revile the Scripture ſayings? What, would he not have thoſe words Printed or read? would he take away thoſe Scriptures for fear the Prophane ſhould abuſe them? Nay, ought they not to be taken away, (as I have heard it ſaid of ſome of them, that they reject the Bible, and ſay it's good for nothing, or fit to be burnt, or the like,) if the Doctrine contained in the Pſalmes and Prophets tend to incourage drunkards and Prophane perſons in their ſwearing, and be contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt? If this be not a deſperate deceiver, that durſt thus revile and blaſphene the very words of Scripture, and a man bitterly malitious, that the better to colour over his charge of me therein, witholds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the word ſwearing, by the word confeſſing (as it's explicated in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.11. and <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.11. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.23.) and ſo a man not to be liſtened to, but to be accounted accurſed, I know not who is: I might alſo note his errors, in implying, the Diſciples were taught by Chriſt to call God Father, as he is Creator, and not as born of God, and that ſome thing in the Diſciples, but not the Diſciples themſelves called Father, but they praying, in that, received what forgiveneſs they asked, but it ſeems were not to aske that dayly as they did their bread, for when they received what they asked, then they had to more ſin, nor need to pray for forgiveneſſe: And ſo he implies, that before they were born of God, or could by the Holy Ghoſt call Father, before the Birth was brought forth in them, they might pray for forgiveneſſe; as when our Saviour teacht them to call God Father, and yet to pray for forgiveneſſe. A deal of ſuch confuſed Babyloniſh ſtuffe <hi>George</hi> is full of.</p>
            <p>A gaine in asking, <hi>Why Chriſt ſhould teach his to pray that his will may be perfectly done in Earth, as it is in Heaven, if it be not in this world to be done.</hi> He implies there is nothing to be prayed for, but what is here to be enjoyed in this world, and ſo would exclude the coming of Chriſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110700:19"/>in glory, and his glorious Kingdome out of our Prayers, for that is in the world to come. But ſure that world is neither in G. W's. Faith nor hope, and how ſhould it be in his Prayers, nor is that the end with him of preaching and praying, ſeeing he implies that if it be not to be had in this world, <hi>It's againſt the end for which the Diſcples of Chriſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as he taught them.</hi> His calling me, <hi>Scornful tempter and blind unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever,</hi> for ſaying, if the <hi>Quakers</hi> have no ſin in them, let them manifeſt it by living without bread. I paſſe as proceeding from his Gall, and tell him there is difference between Chriſts and other mens caſes. He was made under infirmities for our ſins ſake, but if any of us have no ſin, I know no reaſon why we ſhould be infirme, nor find I any thing from Chriſt, that implies men ſhall need to pray for dayly bread longer than for forgiveneſſe of and keeping from ſin; yea even then when the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples are come to that perfect charity, as to make their own forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of others, a rule after which they deſire God to forgive, yet they are willed yet to aske forgiveneſſe of God, and that is a ſtate above G. W's. who is ever and anon at his bitter words, and reproaches, as the Reader of him may ſee.</p>
            <p>His asking, <hi>How men may be kept from ſin, if they may not be kept from it, according to me?</hi> Intimately charges a lye upon me, or diſcovers great ignorance and deceit in him. <hi>David</hi> was kept from his iniqni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet he calls it his iniquity, a man that hath ſin in him may be kept from its getting dominion over him, as <hi>David</hi> implies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12, 13. And from committing it, or conſenting to it, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, when he ſaith, it was no more he that did it, but ſin that dwelt in him. That <hi>Their roote is rottenneſſe though they be appointed as a judgement,</hi> is as underſtandable as that the <hi>Caldeans</hi> were wicked and unholy, and yet ordained for judgement of God; And as their being unholy hindre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not the holyneſſe of Gods Judgement, ſo neither doth the rottenneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe mens roots at all reflect upon the ſoundneſſe of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſeeing he makes uſe of wicked men, whoſe roots are rottenneſſe, to be for his rods and judgements. Laſtly, to his caſting the lye upon me, in what I related of their uncivil and impudent poſting me up, as going away to avoid them, becauſe he ſaies, thoſe words were not in it. I anſwer, what if thoſe very expreſſe words were not in it? things may be couched in expreſſions, where the very ſame words are not expreſly mentioned, as the Doctrine of the Reſurrection of Chriſt ſhewed to be in <hi>Moſes</hi> doctrine, though the word Reſurrection is not expreſſed therein: their words in what they poſted, were thus. <hi>This is to give notice that the ſaid I. H. was lawfully called</hi> (which was falſe, for a call to break promiſe was not lawfull) <hi>by the Q. whom he ſo accuſed, ſo publickly to prove, if he could, what he ſo promiſed, and that he had ſufficient notice, being three daies aforehand of the time, wherein we deſired to meet him,</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo their falſehood and wikedneſſe appears. Their falſhood, for I had notice but the day before they came, whereas I was to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice two or three daies before that. Their wickedneſſe, in that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110700:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>they would dave tyed me to have met them on the Saturday, which I knew muſt have been on purpoſe to ſpend me, that I might have been diſabled from preaching the following day) <hi>But in ſtead of performing his promiſe</hi> (mind) <hi>againſt the Q. he the ſaid I. H. went out of the Town, and ſo hath not performed his promiſe againſt the Qua.</hi> (which is falſe, for I did not promiſe to do it at their next coming, but expreſly excepted againſt it, becauſe of my fore-ingaged journy) <hi>neither can he.</hi> And a little after, they ſay, <hi>People hereby may diſcerne the diceit of theſe men, how having ſpread many rayling and falſe accuſations againſt the Q. when they are tryed, have refuſed to meet us publikely.</hi> Now Reader, compare theſe ſhameful falſities, and ſee if they amount to leſſe than an impudent ſuggeſtion, that I went out of Town, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe making good my charge; which that I have made good through the ſtrength of God, both my former relation and this vindication of it clearly teſtify. What they note as lies in me, ſtand firme for truths, both as to my aſſertions, ſo far as aſſerted by me, without his altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and as to my charges of them, as is made manifeſt, and <hi>George</hi> and the <hi>Quakers</hi> are found clearly to be the Deceivers and Lyers, as in theſe following particulars amongſt others, in ſaying or imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I have not proved my charge, but bragged of a victory where was none.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they come as the Apoſtles, becauſe they have confeſſed fins, though now they do not as they (the Apoſtles) did, when Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they (the <hi>Quakers</hi>) have forſaken their ſins, yet they are found in lies and bitterneſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the judgements of God are ſuch (as his judgements) as the nature of the things or perſons that be uſed by him as Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That <hi>David</hi> boaſted of finleſneſſe in him, where he calls iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty his.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That they that ſay the Saints have ſin in them, plead for ſin, and ſo they make the Apoſtles and Prophets pleaders for ſin.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the Apoſtles were without ſin in this world, as Chriſt is, contrary to their own ſayings in 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8, 10. and 2.1, 2. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That not whoſoever believes Jeſus to be the Chriſt, is born of God, for many, he ſaies, believe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that are not born of God; contrary to 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the Apoſtles and Prophets when they confert ſins, were not true believers, nor born of God.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Nor the Diſciples when Chriſt taught them to call God Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That ſome men living are ſo ſinleſſe in themſelves, that if God ſhould enter into judgement with them, yet they may be juſtified in Gods ſight, contrary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:110700:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="12">12. That <hi>Aſa</hi>'s heart was perfect all his daies, but not all his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That perſons of no judgement or right underſtanding, can affirme or deny nothing, contrary to <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.22.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That Chriſt's coming from Heaven ſpoken of 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16, 17. is either often in diverſe ages, or elſe over and paſt already.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That the Redemption of the body waited for, and groaned after by the Apoſtles and Saints, they had it in this life, before they deceaſed.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That the Saints waited not for things to be given them many hundred years after, contrary to <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13, 39, 40.</p>
            <p n="17">17. That our looking for the coming of Chriſt from Heaven perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and viſibly, to raiſe the dead Saints that are bodily dead, is but our imagination, and a carnal looking for him.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That the coming of Chriſt mentioned, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15. is but a revelation of Chriſt to the Saints, from glory to glory.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That men in whom ſin is, are not, or cannot be, while ſuch, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That to have ſin in men, and to be in thoſe ſins, is all one.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That the 63. <hi>Pſalm verſe</hi> 11. tends to encourage Drunkards, and Prophane perſons in ſwearing, which is contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like be his intimations, as is before more fully ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The Lord deliver the Reader from ſuch deceits, and make the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of theſe men yet more evident, that poor Souls may not be ſnared by them. I ſhall adde no more to G. W. but leave him to the Lords convincement and ſilencing: Who when he ſets home his repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to any of them, will do it to ſuch purpoſe, as to ſtop their clamorous cavils, which they ceaſe not to invent and raiſe up againſt us, though againſt our cleareſt confutations of them, becauſe they be abſurd and unreaſonable men. The Lord exalt his Name and truth, to the rebuke and ſilence of their errors againſt him.</p>
            <div type="queries">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:110700:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queries ſent by</hi> Richard Hubberthorne, <hi>to us, with our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to them; And the like number of Queries ſent by</hi> I. H. <hi>to</hi> Richard Hubberthorne, <hi>to be anſwered plainly by him.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>Richard Hubberthorne <hi>ſent theſe enſuing Queries to us, thus entituled.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Theſe few Queries, grounded upon the Scriptures, concerning the reſurrection of the body of Chriſt, I ſend unto you to Anſwer in the form of ſound words, according to your Faith in the ſame.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1 SEeing the Scripture ſaith, no man Aſcended up to Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven, even the Son of man, which is in Heaven, with what body was the Son of man then in heaven, when the man Chriſt Jeſus was upon the Earth, in that boy which was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. And when Chriſt was raiſed from the dead, whither might any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> before he was Aſcended to the Father, ſeeing he ſaid unto <hi>Mary,</hi> touch me not, for I am not yet Aſcended to my Father, but go to my brethren, and tell them I Aſeend to my Father, and your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to my God and your God? <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.17.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And whether at the ſame time, did not the ſame <hi>Mary</hi> touch him, ſeeing that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.9. it is ſaid ſhe met Jeſus, ſaying, <hi>All hail,</hi> and held him by the feet and worſhiped him?</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Whether the two men that ſtood by the Sepulchre in ſhining gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or white apparrel, as in <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4. which they both ſaw as men, and heard them ſpeak, had two real individual diſtinct bodies, as the bodies of men; and ſeeing that thoſe two men, and alſo Jeſus is ſaid all to appear in white Linnen or ſhining apparrel, whether had they all bodies alike of fleſh and bones, which a Spirit hath not, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39. or they only had ſuch bodies as a Spirit hath, without fleſh and bones?</p>
                     <p n="5">5. And how did the women diſtinguiſh which was Chriſt, whether by his bodily appearance, not to be like the other, or by the power of his voice, ſeeing they all was both ſeen and heard, and <hi>Mary</hi> when ſhe firſt ſaw him, knew him not till he firſt ſpake to her, <hi>John</hi> 20.16. and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that both the Angels and Chriſt, ſpake the ſame words to <hi>Mary,</hi> whereby did ſhe diſtinguiſh?</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Again ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, that the ſame women, at the ſame time found not the body of Chriſt, but returned and ſaid, they had ſeen a viſion of Angels, which ſaid that he was alive, as <hi>Luke</hi> 24. <hi>Ch.</hi> at the 23. whether was it only a viſion of Angels ſeen inviſible, or it was viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bodies or perſons of men, or viſible voices?</p>
                     <p n="7">7. And ſeeing the Scripture ſaith in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.7. That they ſhould go in <hi>Gallilee,</hi> and there ſhould ſee him, whether did the eleven Diſciples firſt ſee him at <hi>Gallilee</hi> or at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſeeing that <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110700:21"/>that the ſame day in which he did ariſe, he appeared in the midſt of them, where the eleven were met together in <hi>Jeruſalem, ver.</hi> 33. and <hi>John</hi> 20.19. it is ſaid, the ſame day at evening, being the firſt day of the week, when the doors were ſhut Jeſus ſtood in the midſt of them? here is the eleven mentioned to be met together, and yet it is ſaid that <hi>Thomas</hi> was not among them, <hi>John</hi> 20.24. And after the eight daies in which he appeared to them again: Whether in all this time had he Aſſended to his Father and their Father, to his God and their God?</p>
                     <p n="8">8. And whether is not all theſe things myſtery, and cannot be ſeen nor known nor underſtood as they are, but as the Spirit doth open and reveal them?</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Richard Hubberthorne</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Theſe for <hi>John Horne</hi> and <hi>Thomas More</hi> to anſwer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>Note here Reader, 1. That the form of ſound words is according to our Faith in the Reſurrection of Chriſt: So the Title perfixed by him implies, and that is rightly implyed, though hapily more than he intended, therein he ſpake truth like as <hi>Caiaphas</hi> did.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That they are not of our Faith, and ſo not of a ſound faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Reſurection of the body of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That he ſaies theſe Queries be concerning the Reſurrection of the body of Chriſt. And yet the firſt ſpeaks of what Chriſt ſaid, while he was not yet put to death, or riſen from it. And in all the reſt he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies his curioſity and evil deſigne, to render the Scriptures but a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly deviſed fable or Allegory, having no real truth in them, in what they ſpeak about that Reſurrection: and to that he believes neither it nor them according to their Teſtimony concerning it, but endevours to render them, not to be regarded or believed according to their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as being full of contradictions and abſurdities, that ſo people might wave them, and learn the myſtery from the <hi>Quakers.</hi> Such wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is clearly enough to thoſe that have the eyes of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding opened, touched in thoſe Queries, as the eighth more clearly implyeth.</p>
                     <p>To theſe Queres I <hi>J. Horne</hi> returned this following anſwer, which I alſo prepared for him, and had in readineſſe to have ſent him, upon the receit of his anſwers to my eight Queries after mentioned, which ſeeing I have not hitherto received from him, I have now made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, as followeth.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To the firſt I ſay, That the Scripture in <hi>John</hi> 3.13. Doth not ſay, that Chriſt was in Heaven in his body then, and therefore that Queſtion (in what body was the Son of man then in Heaven) is not grounded on the Scripture, <hi>Paul</hi> was wrapt up into the third heaven, when yet his body was upon earth. Men may be in their minds and ſpirits where their bodies are not, as <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. much more might Chriſt,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110700:21"/>who was alſo God. He as God, or the eternal Word, was then in heaven and in his Spirit aſcended up to heaven, ſo as no man elſe could, even when his body was upon the Earth and not in heaven, as now it is.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To the ſecond I ſay, ſome might touch Chriſt when he was raiſed from the dead, before he was aſcended and taken up in his body into heaven, there to be and remain, for the confirmation of their faith in the reality of his Reſurrection, though he ſaid to <hi>Mary,</hi> taking hold of his feet to worſhip him, touch me not, for I am not yet aſcended, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.9. with <hi>John</hi> 20.17. For the Diſciples were bid, to the end aforeſaid, to handle and touch him, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.39. <hi>John</hi> 20.27.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To the third I ſay, It's probable <hi>Mary</hi> did at the ſame time touch him, and intended to worſhip him with Divine adoration, &amp; that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned his ſaying to her, touch me not, even as <hi>Cornelius</hi> fell down at <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> feet to worſhip him, and worſhipt him, and <hi>John</hi> fell down to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Angel, and both were thereupon forbidden by them ſo to do, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. To the fourth, The two Angels that ſtood by the Sepulchre in ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning garments, or white apparrel, &amp;c. were, two Angels, and had two individual formes, but that they had bodies as the bodies of men, of the ſame ſubſtance with them, the Scripture ſaies not, nor do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it. Nor find I it ſaid, that Jeſus appeared to his Diſciples after his Reſurrection in white or ſhining garments, or that he and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels had bodies alike of fleſh and bones, which a ſpirit hath not, nor that a ſpirit hath a body without fleſh and bones, or a body at all other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then it aſſumes a body, or appearance of a body to appear in. And the inquiring and prying into theſe things about what is written argues a proud Luciferian ſpirit, and a man raſhly puft up with fleſhly minde not holding the head, or an Atheiſtical deriding (and deſigne to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine) the authority of the Scriptures. There is enough in what is revealed to buſy ourſelves about, and no need to inquire of things kept ſecret, as <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. To the fifth, That the women did diſtinguiſh which was Chriſt, is certain: but how they did ſo, is curioſity to inquire, and perſumption to determine, one of the fooliſh and unlearned queſtions, which we are to avoid, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.23. He that could appear to them in divers forms as he pleaſed, could alſo appear in ſuch a form, as in which they might know him, when he pleaſed, and in ſuch a form when he pleaſed, as in which they did not know him; as to <hi>Mary,</hi> and the two Diſciples go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Enimaus,</hi> or he could open their eyes to diſcerne him, or hold them from it as he would. The like may be ſaid for his ſpeech, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.16.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The ſixth, The Angels, of whom the women had a viſion, were ſeen viſibly without doubt, for of ſeeing inviſibly I have not heard, except in ſuch a fence, as the ſeer be not ſeen again, which was not their caſe. Nor were thoſe Angels bodies or perſons of men, much leſſe had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110700:22"/>they viſible voices, as is ignorantly and non-ſenſically queried. Viſible voices and audible colours are both alike.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. To the ſeventh, in which are ſeveral Queries, I ſay, 1. That the 11 Diſciples ſaw him after his Reſurrection at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> before they ſaw him at <hi>Galilee,</hi> for at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> they ſaw him the ſame day he aroſe. But <hi>Galilee</hi> was above a daies journey thence, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.44. much leſſe could they, being in mortal bodies, go thither and returne again to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the ſame day.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To what is ſaid, That <hi>Luke</hi> 24.33. He appeared where the 11 were met together, And yet it's ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 20.24. That <hi>Thomas</hi> was not there with them.</p>
                     <p>I Anſwer, It's clear, That <hi>Luke</hi> mentions together the things of two appearances to them diſtinctly mentioned by <hi>John.</hi> And yet, 2. It's not ſaid in <hi>Luke</hi> that the 11 were together when he appeared, but when the two diſciples returned. How knoweſt thou but after that, <hi>Thomas</hi> might be gone out before Chriſts appearing. 3. <hi>Thomas</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one of the 12. <hi>John</hi> 20.24. <hi>Mathias</hi> was choſen into their number, and reckoned with them before the Evangeliſts wrote thoſe books though not before thoſe appearances, it may be, and the Evangeliſts might ſpeak of them according to their preſent accompt of them, when he wrote that book. And ſo <hi>Thomas</hi> (who was one of the 12 when the Evangeliſts wrote) being abſent, there were beſides him but 11 of the 12.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. As for his Aſcending to his Father, before that time; poſſibly he might be ſaid in ſuch fence, as in <hi>John</hi> 3.13. to have aſcended more than once; yea, frequently in his ſpirit, but in the moſt proper ſenſe of his body going up thither, there to be contained or received till the time of reſtitution of all things, he was not as then aſcended.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. To the eighth, If by my ſtory you mean, that theſe are not to be taken as they are ſpoken of, I deny it. They are a hiſtory or relation of things not now to be ſo done, or ſo ſeen now as then they were done and ſeen. Though the uſefulneſſe of them is not to be known and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, but by the Spirits opening it to us, in his Teſtimony concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and giving us an underſtanding therein. But herein the <hi>Q's</hi> corrupt judgement is ſeen, that they imply, that they believe not that there was ever any ſuch things really done or ſeen; And ſo that they are very Atheiſtical, not believing further than their reaſon can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, and therefore where they judge it abſurd (as generally they do the truth of Chriſt) they turne it into a fancie, and believe nothing really as it is recorded.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Written by</hi> J. Horne,</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>April 19. 1660.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="queries">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:110700:22"/>
               <head>Eight Queries propounded to <hi>Richard Hubberthorne,</hi> by <hi>John Horne,</hi> to which his plain anſwer is deſired, accord-to his real mind in them.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p n="1">1. IF the believing Samaritans did know rightly, and by the Spirit of truth, that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> as then come in the fleſh, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Chriſt, the Saviour of the world, <hi>John</hi> 4.42. and if <hi>Paul</hi> was a true Apoſtle and preacht the truth, when he proved that that Jeſus is the very Chriſt. And Chriſt himſelfe ſaid truely, that his fleſh is meat indeed, and his blood drink indeed, <hi>John</hi> 6.53, 54, 55. And the ſpirit of truth witneſſes Chriſt come in the fleſh, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.2. How canſt thou clear thy ſelfe of being a Deceiver and falſe Teacher, in ſaying and publiſhing, that Chriſts coming in the fleſh was but a Figure?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. What but a ſilly deceiver was he (G.W. in his anſwers to the <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> Queries) who in juſtification of thy ſaid ſaying, alledged, that Chriſt was transfigured? Might it not as well by the ſame reaſon be touched, that the Apoſtles and Believers were but forms of men, or of godly men, becauſe transformed in the renewing of their minds? <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And if Chriſts coming in the fleſh was but a figure, whether doſt thou believe indeed that that Chriſt, or Jeſus, was a reall man conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a real humane body and ſoul, that had in his body real fleſh and blood, really and verily conceived in the natural womb of a corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Virgine; A Virgine in ſuch ſenſe as other Virgines be before married to, or carnally known by any man, and born really of her into the world: or doſt thou rather believe all thoſe things to be only Allegorically ſpoken?</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And if thou doſt believe that that Jeſus the very Chriſt was indeed a real &amp; perſonal man, whether doſt thou believe that he really and verily and in a real and very body of fleſh dyed, and roſe in the ſame real and very body the third day from the dead, and therein after 40 daies converſing by times with his diſciples aſcended or was taken up into heaven; and be thoſe things alſo only figuratively to be taken?</p>
                     <p n="5">5. And whether doſt thou believe that the ſufferings or dyings of that man in any ſuch real body of fleſh, and his riſing again in the ſame body and aſcending, is truly availeable to the taking away or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring pardon for any mans ſin, and obtaining bleſſing and ſalvation for men? or doſt thou thy ſelf believe to be ſaved from thy ſin and from deſtruction by vertue thereof, yea, or nay?</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Whether doſt thou indeed believe, that there are any Angels or created ſpirits diſtinct from men, and what is in men, and in other viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creatures, yea, or nay?</p>
                     <p n="7">7. And if neither the bodies of men that die, and go to the grave, ſhall ever be raiſed out of their graves to a ſenſible life again,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110700:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>nor (as <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> implies in ſome queſtions ſent us) the ſouls of the wicked after death ſhall come out of Hell again, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any further judgement: Whatof the wicked ſhall be raiſed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain after their bodily death and judged to eternal puniſhment, as <hi>John</hi> 5.29. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46. Is it any thing, or nothing? and if any thing, What is it?</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Doth the ſoul of the wicked at, or after the bodily death, go to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hell in which they ſuſtain or feel any torment? and if ſo, what is the hell they go to, and are tormented in?</p>
                     <p>I challenge thee, to return me, if thon dareſt, a plain and direct an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to theſe queries, according to the very truth and belief of thy heart, not giving revilings inſtead of anſwers, but obſerving, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>John Horne.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>This was ſent him <hi>April</hi> 19. to which I have as yet received no anſwer from him this fourteenth of <hi>May,</hi> ſo that I hope, his mouth is ſtopt with them: However for any plain poſitive and ſober anſwer.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>John Horne</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Richard Hubberthornes <hi>Letter in anſwer to my Queries, is thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>London <date>6th. <hi>day</hi> 4th. Mon. 1660.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>John Horne.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Have received a paper of Queries from thee, by which it is eaſily known to be thine, by thy preface of lies, which is thy uſual and accuſtomed manner, and marke of the beaſt (in all thy papers) thou ſaieſt I am guilty of ſeven or eight falſhoods, but doſt not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of them; neither doſt anſwer my paper, which proves to the contrary: So thou being ſo often reproved, and yet hardens thy heart againſt it, ſo, if thou wilt be filthy, thou maiſt be filthy ſtill, and if thou wilt be unconvinced, when the truth hath been ſo plainly and often declared unto thee, thou mayſt be wicked ſtill.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> As unto thy firſt query, I can clear my ſelf from being a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or falſe Teacher in all things which I have ſpoken; and can alſo prove thee to be a falſe accuſer (in ſaying) that I ſaid &amp; publiſhed, that Chriſts coming in the fleſh was but a figure, which thing I never ſaid, nor publiſhed, and ſo thy query is grounded upon a lye: But thoſe that did ſay and publiſh that falſhood of me, was thy brethren the hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and deceivers at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> and ſo thou takes their lies to be a ſtrength unto thy own. And as for the believing <hi>Samaritans,</hi> they did know by the ſpirit of truth that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> as then come in the fleſh, was indeed the Saviour of the world; and <hi>Paul</hi> was a true Apoſtle, when he proved that Jeſus was the very Chriſt, as <hi>Acts</hi> 9.22.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110700:23"/>And that which Chriſt himſelfe ſaid, in the firſt of <hi>John</hi> 4. and 2. was true; but what is all that unto thee, to ground thy lye upon, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for thy ſecond query, calling <hi>George Whitehead</hi> a ſilly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, for juſtifying of my ſaying, in his anſwer to <hi>Cambridge</hi> queries; What <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> ſaid in that anſwer to <hi>Cambridge</hi> Queries was truth, and was a queſtion put forth unto them, which neither they, nor thou, haſt anſwered, which Query was this: Could Chriſt have been ſaid to have been transfigured, if his coming in the fleſh had not been a figure, or example till his glory was revealed? &amp; haſt thou not read that he was the expreſſe figure of his Fathers ſubſtance, inſtead of which it is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, he is the expreſſe image? &amp;c. And if thou wilt prove him a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, firſt, deny what he hath ſaid, or that it is ſo written, which if thou do affirme, thou goeſt but about to turne the truth of God into a lye, and if thou do confeſſe, thou ownes what <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> hath ſaid, and ſo not prove him a deceiver; and as for thy reaſon to contradict it, which is that the Apoſtles and believers were but forms of godly men, becauſe transformed in the renewing of their minds, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. In this thou haſt appeared very ignorant, void of reaſon and true compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; for the Apoſtles and believers were neither in the power nor form of godly men before the renewing of their minds, but were children of wrath, and were in the form and power of wicked men.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Againe, Thy third Query is grounded upon the ſame lye with the firſt, if Chriſts coming in the fleſh be but a figure, which was never ſpoken by me, nor any of us, but if we ſhould ſay that Chriſt was an example, or was the expreſſe figure of the Fathers ſubſtance, yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we do not ſay, that Chriſts coming in the fleſh is but a figure.</p>
                     <p>And as for my belief of Jeſus, he was real man, and had a real body prepared for him, and in it both ſoul and ſpirit, power and life, which was immortal and Eternal, in which body was real fleſh and blood, and was born of the Virgine according to the Scripture.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to the fourth Query, that which thou querieſt of me, thou doſt not believe thy ſelfe, that Chriſt in that very body of fleſh and blood and bone in which he ſuffered did ariſe again, but thou ſaiſt, with fleſh and bone without blood he is in heaven; ſo then, not with that real and very body born of the Virgine, which thou ſaiſt is real fleſh and blood, and ſo according to thy own writings, not the ſame: But we do believe, that in the very ſame real body in which he after his reſurrection did converſe with his Diſciples, is aſcended into heaven.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> To thy fifth Query I ſay, That the ſuffering and dying of that man Jeſus, and his aſcending into heaven, is truly available unto thoſe which do receive him; by which their ſins are taken away, and they ſaved from deſtruction, but thoſe that do not receive him, but reject him, his light and ſpirit, his ſuffering, dying and riſing again, and aſcending, is not available to the taking away, or procuring pardon for their ſins, for by their rejection of him, to teach and lead
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110700:24"/>them into all truth, they make his blood and all his works, unto them as of none effect.</p>
                     <p>To thy ſixth Query, wherein thou asks whether I do believe there are any Angels or created ſpirits diſtinct from men, and from what is in man, and other viſible creatures.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whether wouldeſt thou have any to believe above what is written, or where doſt thou read, that there is any created Angels or created ſpirits diſtinct from God, which is in man, and from all other viſible creatures, if thou canſt ſhew me any ſuch Angel or created ſpirit which is diſtinct, both from him which did create it, and from all other things created, then thou ſheweſt ſome ground for ſuch a faith, but the Scripture is not a rule for any ſuch faith, neither doth it ſpeak any ſuch thing, and herein thou wouldeſt appear wiſe (or manifeſt thy ſelf a fool) above what is written, and not as one that would be inſtructed, though thou be ignorant.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the ſeventh Query, That which ſhall riſe again after death out of the graves, is the Seeds, and each Seed with its own body, for there are two ſeeds, and two bodies, which ſhall ariſe, the one into Everlaſting life, the other into condemnation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the eighth Query, The Souls of the wicked at death go to a Hell where torment is, felt, which is the eternal wrath of God, the juſt recompence of reward to all hypocrites hirelings and deceivers, who have not only refuſed to receive the truth in the love of it, but have alſo ſet themſelves in enmity againſt it, and this ſhalt thou alſo know hereafter better than thou doſt now, and here is an anſwer retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto thee without railing according to (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.)</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Richard Hubberthorne.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Reply to</hi> Richard Hubberthornes <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough there is no end of controverſing with evil ſpirits, nor the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers ſent by <hi>R. Hubberthorne</hi> need no Reply, the very comparing them with the queſtions they relate to, being a ſufficient diſcovery of <hi>Richards</hi> erroneouſneſſe in them, to thoſe that are intelligent, yet for the ſakes of ſome weaker ones, and to ſtop the mouths of the deceived, I ſhall note his falſhoods and deceits therein. 1. His falſhoods: as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It's falſe, That I had in my paper a Preface of lies. My Preface was thus, <hi>Richard Hubberthorne,</hi> I once received a letter from thee, and I gave thee an anſwer to it, in which I noted thee guilty of 7 or 8 falſhoods, thou didſt return me an anſwer to it, but didſt neither there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in confeſſe thy evils nor diſprove them, ſo that I might ſlight thee as a proved lyer. In that anſwer I remember I took notice of ſome corrupt paſſages about the Reſurrection of Chriſt, by which I am ſatisfied in part that thou art out of the truth; yet becauſe thou ſhouldeſt not think, nor thy party vapor (as one of them yeſter night began to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110700:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuggeſt) that I am afraid to anſwer thee. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Thou having not multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed thy queſtions to very many, I ſhall be willing for this once to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thee an anſwer to them, provided that thou wilt plainly and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly anſwer me in the like number propounded by me, to thee; and when thou ſendeſt thy anſwers to them, to me, thou ſhalt God willing have mine, to thine, returned by me; this was what he calls my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, of the truth of which in every particular, I call God to witneſſe between us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It's falſe, that it's my uſual and accuſtomed manner, and the marke of the beaſt in all my papers to make prefaces of lies, a thing ſaid of him without proof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's falſe, that I ſaid he is guilty of 7 or 8 falſhoods, for my words were not ſo, but that in his former letter (which was ſome years ſince ſent me) I noted him guilty of 7 or 8 falſhoods, that he is guilty now of them, and repented none of them ſince, I affirmed not.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's falſe that his paper proves to the contrary, for neither is his paper in being, and ſo now proves nothing, nor did it, when in being, take notice of thoſe falſhoods that I charg'd him with, ſo as to diſprove them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It's falſe, that I brought as a reaſon to contradict <hi>G. Whitehead's</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured proof, that the Apoſtles and believers were but forms of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, becauſe transformed in the renewing of their minds, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. for that was not my reaſon, nor my aſſertion, but by ſaying was my way of queſtion. Might it not as well by the ſame reaſon, be avouched, that the Apoſtles were but formes of men or of Godly men, becauſe transformed into the renewing of their minds,</p>
               <p n="6">6. It's falſe, that in that ſaying of mine I appeared very ignorant, void of reaſon &amp; true compariſon, for I appeal to all intelligent men, whether the word transformed, applyed to the believers, ſignifies not every jot as much, that they were before, or then alſo, but forms, as that the word transfigured, applyed to Chriſt, proves that he was, or his coming in the fleſh, a figure, or but a figure; Beſides, that he left out part of my ſaying, for I ſaid, forms of men or of godly men.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Falſe it is too, that the Apoſtles or believers, before that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of them in the renewing of their minds, mentioned and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, were neither in the forme nor power of godly men, but were children of wrath and in the power and form of wicked men, for when the <hi>Romans</hi> were exhorted to be transformed in the renewing of their minds (which as it was a thing but exhorted to, they had not as then; for exhortations reſpect things, things yet to be done when ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations are given) they, thoſe <hi>Romans,</hi> were believers and Saints and in part renewed, as appears in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7, 8, 12.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It's a groſſe falſhood, that he ſaies in his anſwer to <hi>Qu.</hi> 4. that I do nor believe myſelf, what I query therein of him: and as,</p>
               <p n="9">9. Falſe too that he charges me with querying, whether Chriſt in that very body of fleſh blood and bone, in which he ſuffered, did ariſe again.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110700:25"/>My words were not ſo, but whether in a real and very body of fleſh he dyed, and roſe in the ſame real and very body the third day.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Falſe it is again that he ſaies, I ſay with fleſh and bone without blood he is in heaven, for I have no ſuch ſaying, nor have ſo determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of it.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Falſe it is too, that he in his next words implies, that if he be not in heaven with fleſh blood and bones, then not with that real and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body born of the Virgine, for he was laid into the Sepulchre in that very body born of the Virgin, and not with another, when as yet his blood was before ſhed out of that body: the body and blood are ſpoken of as diſtinct things, and his body, was his body, and the ſame body in which the blood was, while alive, when in the Sepulchre the blood was not in it; and ſo the ſame body may be in heaven, and is, that was born of the Virgine, though it have not all the ſame things in it that it had when born, as not the ſame weakneſs, littleneſs, mortality, the ſame body that was peirced with a ſpear, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the iſſuing out of it's blood was after it's blood was out laid in the Sepulchre, and the ſame it was laid in the Sepulchre, aroſe and aſcended, though not in the ſame condition for it had no life in it, when it was laid in, it had when it aroſe and aſcended; yet dead and living the body was the ſame.</p>
               <p>Falſe it is too that I ſaid, his body born of the Virgin is real fleſh and blood, I had no ſuch expreſſions; my expreſſion was, that his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy born of the Virgin had in it real fleſh and blood, not is (now at preſent) fleſh and blood.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Falſe it is, that they (the <hi>Quak.</hi>) do believe, that in the very ſame real body in which he after his reſurrection did converſe with his Diſciples, is aſcended into heaven; for both his eighth queſtion implies that they believe, that what is ſaid about the reſurrection of that body is a miſtery, otherwiſe to be underſtood than as it's recorded: And <hi>G. Fox</hi> &amp; the <hi>Whiteheads,</hi> in their anſwers to us, grant no other body in heaven but the body the Church, and that is not the body of Chriſt, in which he after his reſurrection converſed with his Diſciples, for his Diſciples were the body, the Church, or of it, and not the body dead and raiſed in which he converſed with them. Had he ſaid, they do believe that in ſuch a body, as they imagine him to be raiſed in, they alſo believe he is aſcended into heaven, it might have gone for a truth, as touching their belief; but that they believe, that in that body (even of fleſh and bones, that perſonal body) in which he converſed with his Diſciples after the reſurrection, he is aſcended into heaven, is too broadly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory to their other writings to be true.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Falſe it is, that by my own writings it is not the ſame body that was born of the Virgin, or that dyed, or that is aſcended; for I never writ that it was, or is not the ſame ſubſtance or body, though not in the ſame condition, or have not all the ſame things in it it had when it was born, or dyed.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Falſe it is, that he ſuggeſts of me in anſwer to Quer. 6. as if I had
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110700:25"/>implied ſuch a faith as to believe, that there is any Angel or created ſpirit which is diſtinct both from him which did create it, and from all other things created, if by other, he meanes other from God who created it, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it's falſe that the Scripture is not a rule for ſuch a faith, as ſaies, that there is ſome Angel diſtinct from God that made it, and from all other things created beſides it, for the Scripture is grounded for ſuch a faith as that there is and was an Angel called <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſent from God, and ſo diſtinct from God who created it, as he did all things, and diſtinct from all other creatures, ſo as <hi>Gabriel</hi> was none of the other creatures, nor any other creature was that Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.24.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Falſe it is then, that in that 6th. Query, I would appear wiſe or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt my ſelf a fool above what is written, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="17">17. His anſwer to the 7th. query, about what ſhall riſe is altogether cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and falſe, when he ſaies it's the ſeeds ſhall riſe; whereas the Scripture ſaith the men ſhall riſe, every man in his own order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23.</p>
               <p n="18">18. It's falſe, that here is an anſwer returned without railing according to 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. for he neither balked reviling or railing language in his beginning, nor in his proceedings, nor in his end, as the anſwer it ſelf may witneſſe, nor did he render a reaſon of the hope that is in him, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. but in his anſwer to query 5th. leaves that part of the query unanſwered that required a reaſon of his hope, nor is it at all with meekneſs and fear or reverence, as the Reader may wel perceive. Thus for his falſhoods, a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent number in ſo ſhort an anſwer, beſides what elſe might have been noted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His defects in his anſwers are many too, for beſides what may be ſaid to his denyal of ever ſaying that Chriſts coming in the fleſh was but a figure, and charging it upon ſome about <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> as if raiſed falſely upon him, by them, and that I ſtrengthned my ſelf by their lies, which I might have noted as another falſhood, for I never read that I know, of any of their bookes, but found it charged upon him by the Author of the <hi>Cambridge</hi> queries, and not denyed, but pleaded for by <hi>G. W.</hi> in his anſwer to them, and I took it as a ſufficient evidence of his being guilty of it, that his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther G. undertaking to anſwer that charge, did not deny it, but endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make it good, though but ſorrily, as alſo his anſwer to that ſecond query ſhewes; beſides that, I ſay—</p>
               <p n="1">1. His anſwer to the ſecond query is defective and fooliſh, for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It's ſilly, that he ſaies, what <hi>George Whitehead</hi> ſaid was truth, and yet adds it was a queſtion. Sure if it was a queſtion, it aſſerted nothing, and ſo was neither in it ſelf truth nor falſhood; and if it was an intimate aſſertion by way of queſtion, then it was more then a queſtion ſimply, and ſo it was a falſhood, becauſe what was therein intimately aſſerted, was that Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing transfigured proved his coming in the fleſh a figure, or but a figure, which is no more true, then, that the believers being transformed proves them to have been formes, or but formes, in that part of his anſwer there was fillineſſe or falſhood. To the queſtion I ſay by way of anſwer, Chriſt might have been ſaid to have been transfigured becauſe the form or figure of his countenance was changed, though his coming in the fleſh was no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, or though it had been no example till his glory was revealed, beſides there is this fillineſſe in <hi>G's.</hi> anſwer by the queſtion, that it implies that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110700:26"/>Chriſt was no example for us after he was transfigured, in that he ſaies, till his glory was revealed, namely, in the transfiguration, which is contrary to 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. which tells us he was an example in his ſufferings, which were after he was transfigured.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His ſaying, haſt thou not read, that he was the expreſſe figure of his Fathers ſubſtance, inſtead of which, it is tranſlated, the expreſſe image? &amp;c. is but ſimple, for if it be tranſlated the expreſſe image, how or where ſhould I read it the expreſſe figure? not in the <hi>Greek,</hi> for there it is not figure which is an <hi>Engliſh</hi> word, nor is it ſuch a <hi>Greek</hi> word as is in any other place of the Bible tranſlated figure, and why is it tranſlated image inſtead of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, if the word there uſed, is none of thoſe words elſewhere in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures tranſlated by the word figure? beſides that, he corrupts the text, and ſaies the figure of his ſubſtance, inſtead of the image of his perſon, but what if it had been read, the expreſſe figure of his Fathers ſubſtance? doth that prove his coming was a figure too? ſo then to prove him a Deceiver, I have denyed, and do deny what he ſaies to be true, if in his queſtion he imply affirmatively, either that thoſe words be ſo read, or that they prove <hi>Richards</hi> ſaying that he defends; the falſeneſſe of what he adds, to what he calls my reaſon is before ſpoken to.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His anſwer to my third queſtion prevaricates, for <hi>Rich. Hubberthorne</hi> by <hi>G. Whiteheads</hi> pleading for his ſaying, ſaid more than he ſuppoſes that Chriſt was an example, or the expreſſe figure of the Fathers ſubſtance, but what? is it all one to be an example, and the expreſſe figure of the Fathers ſubſtance that they are put ſo together, as if they amounted to the ſame thing? are all examples then in the Scripture the expreſſe figure of the Fathers ſubſtance? but beſides that, he in anſwering leaves out, and durſt not touch the tearms of my queſtion, as that Jeſus was a real man conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a real humane body and Soul, and that he was really conceived and born in the natural womb of a corporal Virgin, in ſuch fence a Virgin, as other Virgins be, &amp;c. he durſt not ſpeak ſo diſtinctly, but hides himſelf in ſuch general tearmes as might keep him from being ſo eaſily ſeen.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He gives the go by to the fourth queſtion too, and plaies the prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator in the laſt clauſes of it, as is before ſufficiently noted</p>
               <p n="4">4. He hides himſelf in his anſwer to the 5th. and leaves out the latter part of it, for in the former part the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, by which their ſins are taken away, thoſe words (by which) are equivocal, and are ſo ſubtilly placed as he may mean, that by their receiving him, their ſins are taken away and not by the ſuffering and dying of the man Jeſus, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In his anſwer to the ſixth, he plainly enough caſts miſts before his readers eyes, to dazle him, that he might not diſcerne, that he believes no Angles or created ſpirits diſtinct from God and the ſpirits of men, and that are in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſible creatures, and yet his intimate joyning with the <hi>Sadduces</hi> in denying them, appears clearly enough, to thoſe whoſe eyes can ſee through his miſts; for he implyes, it's to believe above what is written, to believe that there are Angels or created ſpirits diſtinct from men, and what is in man, and in other viſible creatures: and by his queſtion, where I read, that there is any created Angels or created ſpirits diſtinct from God, which is in man and from all other viſible creatures; what doth he, but imply his unbelief
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110700:26"/>or denyal of any ſuch thing? To anſwer briefly to the queſtion, I ſay, that though I do not read in juſt ſo many words put together that ſaying, yet I find it clearly in the Scriptures in every part of it, as to ſay, 1. That there are Angels and Spirits, I read in <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7.14. that they are created, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo both there implyed, and in <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.9. where it is ſaid that God created all things by Jeſus Chriſt, and in <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. all things were created by him that are in heaven, and that are in earth, whether viſible and inviſible, &amp;c. ſo then there being ſuch things as Angels and ſpirits, &amp; thoſe Angels things in heaven, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.32. Angels in heaven, and all things in heaven and earth being created of God by Chriſt, it neceſſarily followes, that they be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and created alſo. 3. That they are diſtinct from God, whether as in man, or in heaven, as more uſually he is ſaid to be, is as evident if we firſt ſhew what it is to be diſtinct; now that is diſtinct from another thing that is not that thing, as the Soul is diſtinct from the body, becauſe it is not the body, and the body is diſtinct from the Soul, becauſe it is not the Soul, and the eye is diſtinct from the ſight, becauſe the eye may be without ſight, and the ſervant is diſtinct from the maſter, becauſe he is not the maſter, ſo the Angels are diſtinct from God and Chriſt, becauſe they are not God nor Chriſt, but created by God and Chriſt, and made miniſtring ſpirits, and ſent forth from God to ſuch purpoſe, and that they are diſtinct from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſible creatures, is evident becauſe they are not any of the other creatures viſible or inviſible, but are a diſtinct kind of creature themſelves, diſtinctly named from them, and that have diſtinctly ſome of them appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when made viſible to the ſight of men, without the bodys and beings of all other creatures, as in thoſe that miniſtred to Chriſt, and that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Daniel,</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi> to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and divers others, which were neither properly men, nor women, nor any other creature diſtinct from Angels or miniſtring ſpirits; &amp;c. So that that queſtion implies great igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and unbelief of the Scriptures, as alſo his adding that, if I can ſhew him any ſuch Angel or created ſpirit, that is diſtinct both from him which did create it, and from all other things created, then I ſhow ſome ground for ſuch a faith, this with his changing my words which were diſtinct from men, &amp; from what is in man &amp; in other viſible creatures, into another form, <hi>viz.</hi> diſtinct from him that made them, and from all other creatures implies that he thinks there is no creature but what is viſible or may be ſeen, ſure his other ſenſes may confute ſuch a fancy, for did he ever ſee any mans Soul? or ſee the wind that blows? and yet I trow theſe be creatures, but why will he not believe more then I can ſhew him? Angels be of themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, pitch their tents about men, who yet ſee them not, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.7. with 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6.16, 17. but I have ſhewed him in the Scripture, if he have any eyes of underſtanding to ſee with, that there was, and truly is an Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſent of God, and not God himſelf, who is diſtinct from all other men, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and creatures beſides him, they none of them being him; yea many thouſand ſuch ſhal Chriſt appear with at his coming, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. ſo that his falſhood and impiety appears in what followes in the anſwer as that the Scriptures is not a rule for any ſuch faith, nor doth ſpeak any ſuch thing.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And his Anſwer to the 7th. Query joyned with his former anſwer
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110700:27"/>proves him a direct Sadducee to them that can underſtand him, for as his anſwer to the 6th. denies intimately, and yet plainly enough, that there be many ſuch Angels and Spirits as the Scripture declares, ſo his anſwer to the 7th. denies the reſurrection of the body, as will appear if he will clearly ſpeak out his minde in explication of his ſaid anſwer, for to that query, what it is of men that ſhall riſe again after the bodily death? he anſwers, That which ſhall riſe againe after death out of the grave, is the ſeeds and each ſeed with its own body, for there are two ſeeds and two bodies which ſhall ariſe, the one into everlaſting life, and the other into condemnation, which though it be the moſt poſitive anſwer of any he gives, &amp; freeſt from reviling language, yet cannot be underſtood unleſſe it be known, what be thoſe two ſeeds? whether they be not the wheat and the Tares ſpoken of <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.37, 38? or what elſe they be? and who ſowes, or ſowed them? and when? and where they be ſown? and what be the graves they be in? and whether they be but two ſeeds in all the world over, or two in every man, one the incorruptible ſeed, the other the corruptible ſeed? and whether they be ſown or raiſed after the bodily death of men, or only af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome ſpiritual death of the feeds? for I named after the bodily death, and he leaves out the word bodily, and ſo ſpeaks equivocally: and whether be each of theſe ſeeds a man, ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaies not every ſeed, but every man ſhall riſe in his own order? and whether did the Apoſtle forget one of thoſe ſeeds, when he ſaies, it is ſown in weakneſſe, it is raiſed in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when of two he ſhould have ſaid, they are ſown in weakneſſe they are raiſed in power? and whether is either of theſe ſeeds, when its ſown a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural body, and either of them when they riſe a ſpiritual body, ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaies it is ſown a natural body, it is raiſed a ſpiritual body? and what be the two bodies they ſhall riſe with? are they two in every man? or be they humane bodies, or bodies of men? and why ſaies he the one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting life, the other into condemnation? and why not unto ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life and unto condemnation? and why is not the condemnation ſaid to be everlaſting by him as well as the life? Thoſe things I challenge him for explaining his anſwer before it can be ſeen to agree with the Apoſtles Doctrine of the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For the eighth query, he in his anſwer leaves out the word Bodily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſo tels us not of any hell men go into, or their ſouls, after the death of their bodies; but prevaricates and hides himſelf again: nor proves that eternal wrath ſhall give up any that ſhall be in it, as it's ſaid hell and Death ſhall, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 20.13.</p>
               <p>But if Hell be the reward of all Lyers, Deceivers, Hirelings and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, what will become of <hi>Richard Hubberthorne,</hi> who hath told ſo many falſhoods, and delt ſo deceitfully and hypocritically in thoſe his anſwers; if he repent not, let the Reader judge.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Horne.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110700:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
